<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse, of the true and visible markes of the Catholique Churche vvritten by M. Theod. Beza. Vezelius</title>
            <title>De veris et visibilibus Ecclesiae Catholicae notis. English</title>
            <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09876</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 2014</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101560</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837369</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837369</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1688</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09876)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1688)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 411:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse, of the true and visible markes of the Catholique Churche vvritten by M. Theod. Beza. Vezelius</title>
                  <title>De veris et visibilibus Ecclesiae Catholicae notis. English</title>
                  <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
                  <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[134] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Walde-graue, dwelling without Temple-bar, in the Strond, neere vnto Sommerset-house,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1582?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: T.W., i.e. Thomas Wilcox.</note>
                  <note>Translation of: De veris et visibilibus Ecclesiae Catholicae notis.</note>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [pi] A-G H⁴ (-[pi]1).</note>
                  <note>At least gathering A outer forme is in two settings: page A1r, line 5 ends: (1) "beeyng" or (2) "beeing".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1688:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1688:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> DISCOURSE, OF <hi>the true and viſible Markes</hi> of the Catholique <hi>Churche</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVritten by M. THEOD. BEZA. Vezelius.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device with bird</figDesc>
               <head>GOD IS MY HELPER</head>
            </figure>
            <q>GOD IS MY HELPER. <bibl>Pſal. 7.11</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON; ¶<hi>Printed by Robert Walde-graue, dwelling</hi> without Temple-bar, in the Strond, neere vnto Sommerſet-houſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1688:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1688:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>TO THE</hi> RIGHT <hi>WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull, Sir George</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rey knight, knight <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhall of her Maiesties bouſholde, &amp;c.</hi> T. VV. his poore welwiller, wiſheth <hi>aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of all good thinges in this life, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> bleſſedneſſe in the life to come, through Chriſte.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OVVE glorious and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a thing the church it ſelfe is; may appeare (Right VVorſhipfull) by many meanes: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, euen by this: that all; both good and bad, do challenge and claime (whether juſtly or vnjuſtly, I minde not much novve to diſpute) not onely the name and ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le thereof. but the verie poſſeſſion of it alſo.
<pb facs="tcp:1688:3"/> I hope I ſhall not neede much to buſie my ſelfe in the proofe of this point: Becauſe, as it mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly appeareth, by ſundry examples of former times, and particularly, by the people of the Iewes in the dayes of Ieremiah the prophet: who cried out: The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord: this is the Temple of the Lorde: as is to be ſeene in the ſeuenth chapter of his booke: So haue vve a moſt euident and playne teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the ſame in this declining and doting olde age of the world: For whereabout are thoſe large diſputations which at this daye are handled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvveene the catholiques, as they would be called, and the true profeſſours of Chriſts Goſpel, moſte occupied; I pray you; but ſpeciallye about this queſtion, and other controuerſies concerning the ſame? The thing rather, that in my mind is more to be ſtoode vpon, is this: namely, to ſee: what ſhoulde be the cauſe why, that notwithſtanding that ſame greedye deſire that the greateſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber haue, to retaine with them both the name of the Church, and the Churche it ſelfe: yet ſo fewe haue it &amp; hold it faſt. All men haue in them, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the defacing of God his image in them through ſinne, by ſome ſmall ſparkes of reaſon and iudgement; which yet remayne in them vndefaced, A certaine thirſting after Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes, and the hope of a better life: And this is the more inkindled in mennes hearts and heads, when it pleaſeth God, to vouchſafe them in ſome meaſure of his mercy, ſome light and knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:1688:3"/> of his holy truth: by which they ſee, that with out the Church there can bee no ſaluation. And that cauſeth them to preſſe on forward to vviſh to be of that number that hath ſo gracious a Priuilege graunted vnto the ſame: And yet all this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, it is a vvonder to ſee, how the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of the vvorlde is deceiued, vvith a bare ſhadow and ſhevve of the ſame: For, that I may ſpeake nothing of the Infidelles in their idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; nor of the Turkes, cleauing faſt to their Mahomet; Nor of the Ievves, openly diſpiting Chriſte the Sauiour of the vvorlde: and therefore all of them, of neceſſitye out of the Church, and conſequently void of ſaluation alſo: becauſe they hold not the head, which is Chriſt. To let all theſe paſſe, I ſay, and to come to them vvhich in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard ſhevv make profeſſion of Chriſtianitie and true religion; hovv many of them are there that are violently carried avvaye vvith as groſſe and palpable Idolatrie, as the heathen? VVhat infinite multitudes periſh thorough ignorance, and want of the ſound knovvledge of God in Chriſte? hovv many are drovvned, to the hazarding of their ovvne ſoules, vvith horrible erroures and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies? And what a number are there in the vvorlde beſide, that ſhaking handes, as it vvere vvith A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts (ye the vvorſt people of al) do lye vveltring in the pleaſures and profits of this life; making no account at all, either of God in heauen, or of his Church here in earth? And vvhat would the Lord teach vs by al this: verely firſt that vve muſt haue
<pb facs="tcp:1688:4"/> better eyes to diſcern his congregation by, then the light of our ovvn reaſon: for if euen then vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvee haue his vvorde, vvee can yet hardly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry it, partly becauſe it is diſcerned ſpiritually, and partly becauſe by the hard dealings of the enimies it is ſundry times brought to ſo lovv an eb, that it ſeemeth to be ſhut vp in one mans perſon. And therfore do ſay in the confeſſion of our Chriſtian faith, that vve do beleue that there is a holy catho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lique Churche: that then vve ſhall neuer be able to ſeperate it from the Synagogue of Satan by our ovvne vnderſtanding and vvit: vvhich conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration is yet further profitable; euen for the confutation of that immagination and conceit, which our aduerſaries haue and hold concerning mans freevvil: for if vve cannot by our ovvn co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion perceiue eyther the place in vvhich, or the perſonnes amongſt vvhome, the Church it ſelfe is, but that vvee muſt haue from aboue, for that purpoſe, greate enlightning both of knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and fayth, much leſſe ſhall vve bee able to comprehend thoſe vvonderfull treaſures of moſt ſounde, comfortable, and profitable doctrine that the Lord hath freely beſtovved vppon his ſayde Church: Of vvhich the Apoſtle ſaith: that the eye hath not ſeene them, the eare hath not hearde them, neither can mans heart comprehend them. 2. Cor. 2.9. VVherefore the caſe ſtandeth not vvith vs as heretofore wee haue beene borne in hand: And as yet to this day, is openly defended amongſt Papiſtes: that man in his meere naturall gifts, hath vvill to deſire, and povver to perfourm
<pb facs="tcp:1688:4"/> ſuche thinges as are good: for if it bee God that worketh in vs both the vvill and the deed; &amp; that according to his ovvn good pleaſure. Philip. 2.13. And that vve are not ſufficient of our ſelues, as of our ſelues to thinke a good thought. 2. Cor. 3.5. It muſt needes follovve that vve can not claime any ſuch thing vnto our ſelues, vvithout robbing God of his glorie, without lifting vp of our ſelues aboue meaſure and trueth, and vvithout impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the authoritie and credite of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which in many places affirmeth, and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Geneſ. 6.5. that all the immaginations of the thoughtes of mans heart are only euil euery day: But to let this paſſe, and to come to the thinges we haue in hande, VVe are hereby in the ſecond place inſtructed, that vvee muſte haue more ſure and infallible markes, to knovve God his Churche by, than thoſe vvhich the Papiſtes giue vs, to wit: vniuerſalitie, Antiquitie, and conſent: for if beſide that great number of Idolatours, and misbeleeuers mentioned before; vvho alſo can alleadge for themſelues great antiquity &amp; agree, and (as he that is not vvilfully blinde, may eaſilye ſee) there are, and that euen in the lappe and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the Church, many hypocrites and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques alſo, vvhich yet ſhall not be ſaued: we may then ſafely conclude that the forenamed things are not only not the aſſured notes: but no notes at all rather of the true Church of God: both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are common to many things beſides the Churche; yea euen to euill thinges, and alſo
<pb facs="tcp:1688:5"/> becauſe that though that aſſemblye vvhich pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to bee the Church, ſhoulde haue them; and yet haue not therevvithal the trueth and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie of God his doctrine; it is no vvhit at al the better for all that. All theſe thinges tende to this end: that for as much as in trueth there is but one Churche, euen as the heade thereof is one, and therefore ſo muſt the body be: or elſe it ſhoulde be monſtrous, notvvithſtanding that there bee ſundry particular partes and members thereof, as vvee ſee in a mans body; all yet making but one and the ſelfe ſame body: And foraſmuche alſo, as vvithout that Church there can be no ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe vnto it alone is it; that the Lord hath made ſuch large and gracious promiſes: as; The gates of Hell ſhall not preuayle agaynſte it: and that to it onely belongeth the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes in this life, and euerlaſting ſaluation in the life to come: And laſtly, forasmuch as it behoueth euery one, euen as he tendeth his ovvne peace of conſcience, and regardeth the hope of eternall bleſſednes; to be vvatchfull, in diſcrying and kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vving this Church; and carefull in vniting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto the ſame: euerye good man therefore ſhould earneſtly labour, not onely to knovve it: but alſo ſtedfaſtly, to ioyne himſelfe vnto it in the religious exerciſes thereof: That ſo in the holye feeling of the communion of Saints, he may bee a fruitfull partaker of all thoſe excellent graces that God in great mercie hath bequethed to the ſame. True it is, that Satan, the common enemy
<pb facs="tcp:1688:5"/> of mankinde (vvho in his ovvne perſon, and the perſonne of his inſtruments and miniſters labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to hinder, vvhat he maye, the vvorke of oure ſaluation) hath in all ages vſed, and yet preſently doth vſe manye ſubtile and ſlie ſhiftes, to let vs from the apprehenſion and vnderſtanding of theſe great graces: for ſomtimes he maketh men vtterly and altogether careleſſe of the Churche, and of the benefites and bleſſinges of God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed thereto: As vvee maye ſee in that troup of prophane Atheiſtes and vvorldly minded men: vvho make no more account of the Church, and the holy exerciſes therof; than of a vaine tale, or vnholy matter: no, nor ſo muche neither many times; for the one they embrace vvith greedines &amp; vvonderfull delight; &amp; the other they doe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt diſpitefullie contemne, or moſt negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently vſe vvithout any ſpirituall profite at all vnto themſelues. But to beate dovvne theſe men, there is no better VVeapon &amp; vvay, then to ſend them to the fearefull iudgementes of Almightie God, and to the horrors of hel and eternal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation (which many times they feele in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, though thorough the profites and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this preſent euil vvorlde, they vtterly put them out) already prepared for them, and in due time to be perfourmed to them. Sometimes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, hee diſcourageth men, by ſetting before them the feareful perſecutions and troubles that follovve, and take holde of the particular mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, for the ſyncere profeſſion of
<pb facs="tcp:1688:6"/> God his vvorde: for the ſurmounting of vvhich aſſaulte, men muſte often meditate vppon thoſe ſame large &amp; comfortable diſcourſes that are put dovvn and conteined in God his vvord for their comfort in that behalfe, and to holde them back from the fearful fall of renouncing god his truth, hauing their eye faſt fixed alſo vpon the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar deliuerances, that God in al ages hath vvroght for his children: vvhich are as it vvere ſo manye ſeales ſet vnto the vvriting; that he vvill alvvaies deale ſo graciouſlye vvith his children, as ſhall make moſt for his ovvne glorie. and their eternall comfort. Sometimes he deceiueth other ſomme, and that no ſmall ſome by the bare name and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zor of the Churche alone; as vve may ſee in that miſerable ſect of ſeduced Papiſts (vniuſtly called, and claiming vnto themſelues: the name of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques) vvhoe vvillingly embrace vnder the title of the Churche, euery fabulous falſhood &amp; corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vvhatſoeuer, not only not looking vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the things, giuen or offred: vvhich euery vviſe man vvill doo, leaſt he receiue poyſon in ſteede of vvholſom and nouriſhing foode: but alſo not conſidering the perſonne of the giuer, neither yet vvhat right and authoritie he hath to beſtovv the thinges giuen; vvhich blockiſhneſſe of the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, is rather to be lamented, becauſe it is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether voide of common ſenſe and reaſon, than largely or learnedly confuted: And yet vve ſee that manye good men haue not ſpared to take great paines in that behalfe, both by preaching &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:1688:6"/> vvriting, to vvinne ſeduced ſouls vnto Cod. Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hee ſetteth before other ſome, either the hardneſſe that there is, to diſcrie the true Church from the falſe Church by, (remember I pray you that vvhen I giue the name Church, to corrupted and counterfaited aſſemblies, I do it by abuſion, as they ſay) or elſe layeth out the great iarres and diſſentions, that many times are in the ſame, that ſo he may diſcourage them from ioyning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to that holy ſocietie, And indeede by this aſſault he ſpecially preuaileth againſt them that are in ſome forvvardnes to encline to the truth: And yet by reaſon of ſome certaine vveakeneſſe in them, are eaſely turned the one vvay or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but theſe men, for the better ſtaie of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, are to knovv, that there muſt be hereſies, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen among the godly; that they vvhich are appro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued among them might be knovvne. 1 Cor. 11.19. and to be exhorted; that they labour to abounde in al holy knovvledge of God his vvil reuealed in his vvord; For therefore they erre, and are ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable in their opinions, becauſe they knovv not the Scriptures; nor the povver of God. Novve therefore, neceſſarie is it, that theſe ſtumbling blocks, caſt by Satan &amp; his ſeruants in our vvaies to hinder vs in the race and courſe of Godlines, ſhould be remoued: that ſo vvee maye the more cheerefully and readily goe forevvard vvith faith, patience, and conſtancie, euen to the goal that is ſet before vs. In vvhich reſpect, that excellent inſtrument of God in his Churche; M. Theodor
<pb facs="tcp:1688:7"/> Beza, hah notably trauailed by publiſhing in the Latine tongue; a moſt learned Treatie of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Notes of the viſible Church: And I, for the ſame conſideration, haue according to my ſmall meaſure, faithfully turned the ſame into our vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſpeech, offring theſe my poore trauailes vnto you (right vvorſhipfull) and in you, to the vvhole Church of God in this land; as a ſure teſtimonie of that vnfained good vvill vvhich in the Lorde, I haue carried and vvill carry tovvards you all the dayes of my life. I hope, I ſhall not neede to ſpend many vvords eyther in commending the vvorke it ſelf, or in declaring the reſons that haue moued me to attempt this matter: for if either the man vvho is the author therof, or the matter vvhich is propounded, or the maner that he vſeth in laying out of the thing, may add co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation vnto it, it ſhal not vvant any grace that may bring it into loue and lyking vvith the Godly: for as touching the man himſelfe; hee is euen the miror of the vvorlde in theſe our daies, for true knovvledg and vnfayned godlines, vvhatſoeuer the papiſts doe lyingly and ſlanderouſly babble to the contrarie: And as touching the matter, it is that vvhich ought to be of greateſt accompt amongeſt men, and vvhich euen in reſpect of the bare name and title of it, is verie glorious and excellent much more in reſpect of the ſubſtance thereof it ſelfe: And for the manner of handling the things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, it is ſhort for auoiding of tedioſnes, it is plaine, euen for the capacitie of the ſimple; it is
<pb facs="tcp:1688:7"/> ſound in reſpect of the truthe it propoundeth: And it is ſufficient, not onely to inſtruct God his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo to ſtop vp the aduerſaries mouths in this matter; and vvhat then vvanteth? or vvhat can be more acceptable &amp; profitable? vvherefore I doubt not but it shall haue good entertainment as amongeſt all the godly generally, ſo particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly of your vvorship; vvho I knovv doth harte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loue the Church, and carefully like, and tender the cauſes therof; vvhich alſo hath beene the principall matter mouing me, to vndertake this trauaile, and to dedicate the ſame, vvhatſoeuer it be, vnto your vvorshippe; vvhome (for ſundry good graces, that God hath beſtovved vpon you) I do vnfaynedly loue and reuerence in Chriſte. Humbly praying and earneſtly exhorting you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your meaſure of light and knovvledge receiued from the Lorde, to enforce your ſelfe to the vttermoſt of your habilitie euery maner of vvay to the preferring and promoting of theſe excellent matters, and namely thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the reformation of ſuch corruptions as yet remaine amongeſt vs, either touching the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, or the diſcipline of the Church: for to this ende hath God endued you vvith all the graces that you haue preſently receiued, or may hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thorovv his goodneſſe attaine vnto; eyther of vvit, vvealth, learning, credit, countenance, byrth, office, honor, or vvhatſoeuer els: vvherevnto I vvill (thorovv God his grace) not onely ſtyrre you vp by all the holy and lavvfull meanes I can: but
<pb facs="tcp:1688:8"/> alſo further you in my poore prayers to almighty God in that behalfe; that you may daily encreaſe and continue in the ſounde knovvledge of his truth, in the ſtedfaſt faith of his promiſes, in the ſincere zeale of his glorie, in vnfained loue of his holy vvord and the exerciſes thereof, and in care and conſcience to put in practiſe, thoſe good thinges that are enioyned you therein, that your vvhole life maye tende to the glory of God, the good of the Church and common vvealth, and the faithfull ſeruice of her maieſtie, and your death be comfortable to your ſelfe; as beeing the ſpeedy paſſage to eternall life, and profitable vnto others; vvhile they be by your example in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, both to liue and die vvell: vvhich God graunt for his crucified Chriſt his ſake; To vvhoſe gracious gouernement and good direction, I doe humbly commend your vvorship, and all yours both novv and for euer. London the 16. of this Nouember. 1582.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your worſhips alwaies ready in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus:</hi> T. W. <hi>the Lorde his vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:1688:8"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF THE TRVE AND viſible Notes of the Catholique Church.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>EN demaunde at this daie, concerning the markes and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the church: the queſtion beeyng rayſed by thoſe, who, when they ſee their erroures to bee refelled, by the worde of God, obiecte vnto men, that are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkilfull of theſe matters, the ſacred name of the Church: and by heaping vp the diſputations of auncient fathers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Heretiques, they bring vs into hatred, as though we had corrupted both the bookes of Gods worde, and alſo, as though by violating all authority of the church, we had (after the example of the<note n="[a]" place="margin">They were ſo called of one Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, who baptized ſuch as imbraced his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, though they were baptized be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and made a ſchiſme in the Church, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yeere. 334.</note> 
               <hi>Donatistes</hi>) ſet vp altar againſt altar: to be ſhort, as though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee haue ſhaken of the yoke of <hi>Babilon,</hi> we had
<pb facs="tcp:1688:9"/> forſaken the Church, without the which notwithſtanding (euen as we our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues confeſſe) there is no ſaluation. And neither doth this ſubtle kinde of reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, dryue away the vnſkilfull onely, from the knowledge of the truth, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo cauſeth, ſome euen amongeſt them, which ſéemed moſt ſtedfaſt to wauer. Furthermore, by this occaſion very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny take counſell betwéene both ſides, and as in opinions, they indeuour to mingle light with darkneſſe: ſo alſo in diſcerning of the true Church, they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to mingle the baſtardly or falſe marks, with the true and proper marks therof. But except men would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be deceiued, the deceit of theſe men, might be very eaſely perceiued and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded.<note place="margin">Men muſt firſt define the Church, before they enquire any thing of the authoritye thereof.</note> For, firſt men ſhould demaund, what that Church ſhould be, before they determine of the boundes of hir autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: which order they that doe not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, commit truely that groſſe error, and worthy of ſtripes, which they call<note n="[a]" place="margin">That is, the begging or taking of that as granted: which is in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie</note> 
               <hi>Petitio principij.</hi> Go to then let vs ſée what theſe men meane by the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
<pb facs="tcp:1688:9"/> Church.</p>
            <p>Theſe men holde (what ſo euer they diſſemble) that the Church (in which we ought to abide,<note place="margin">That the Catholique Church is not rightly called euery congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in which is a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</note> if we will be ſaued) is an aſſemblie of Biſhops, whoſe calling and names may bee fet from the Apoſtles them ſelues. We ſay that this ſucceſſion which is meerely perſonall, neyther is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the Church, neither any whit at all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> vnto thoſe that alleadge the ſame.</p>
            <p>That it is not the church, may appear <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> euen vnto very children, firſt by this,<note place="margin">The order of Biſhops is not the church.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnder the name of the church, proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken, it is certain, that not only the Paſtors, but alſo the flocks are compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended: Now it is altogether ridiculous to define a part, as the whole it ſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by that meanes the whole and the parte, ſhoulde be one and the ſelfe ſame thing.</p>
            <p>They reply,<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of a by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and of a flock is not alwayes a note of a true church.</note> that they vnderſtand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Paſtors, the very flocks them ſelues, cleauing vnto them. But this thing is alſo ridiculous, ſéeing that both hereticall, and backeſliding Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> may ſucceed Paſtors of ſound
<pb facs="tcp:1688:10"/> iudgement, and hereticall flockes true <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſheepe: and ſome times in deed the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors are hereticall, and the ſheep true, &amp; contrary wiſe, true paſtors may haue hereticall ſheepe. When that thing fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> out: to wit, that both the Paſtors and the flockes, are heretticall, the very aduerſaries them ſelues dare not deny, but that ſuch a whole Church (although it haue had aunceſtors in deed Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall, &amp; both the Paſtors and the flocks, do agree amongſt themſelues in falling away) is yet notwithſtanding altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a falſe Churche, vnleſſe they will take theſe ſpeeches, to wit, to be hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and vniuerſal, for one and the ſelfe ſame thing. But in the latter caſe, at leaſt wiſe in one part, there is found falſehood, although on both ſides that perſonal ſucceſſion may be found. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore neither the ſucceſſion of perſons by it ſelfe, neither ſuch maner of conſent, doth of neceſſitie prooue a true Church, for as much as, where both are found, yet ſome times there maye be a falſe church: and there in ſome ſort may be a true church, where the paſtor diſſenteth
<pb facs="tcp:1688:10"/> from the ſheepe, or the ſheepe from the paſtor. Now, that men may, by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples both paſt and preſent, prooue that theſe things haue too often times fallen out, no man I ſuppoſe will denie.</p>
            <p>But againe they ſay, that they diſpute not of particular Churches, which they graunt may fall away, but of that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique or vniuerſall Church,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>which is the piller &amp; foundation of truth.</hi> But how I pray you do they define this catholike Churche. Firſte by a certayne place, as <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> thoſe that will haue catholicke and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> to be al one: Secondly, by the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <note place="margin">Catholique and Roman are not all one.</note> as they which vpbraide vs with fewnes. Let vs ſee, therfore what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of arguments theſe be. They be (if they be kept within the iuſt rules of reaſoning) vnleſſe I be deceaued, theſe and ſuch like. The church of <hi>Rome</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth ſo: very many, in reſpect of a very few ſo beleeue, and ſo it was from hand deliuered vnto vs. Therefore this is the catholique truth. But who is ſo far void of all reaſon, that he ſeeth not here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Petitio principij,</hi> and the thing in controuerſie to be taken as graunted?
<pb facs="tcp:1688:11"/> Shew vs therefore, ye Sophiſters, or at leaſt wiſe teach vs probablie, firſte how a part ſhould be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whol (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may graunt vnto you your Romiſh church, to be a principall member of the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke church). And then from whence, I pray you, haue ye learned, this Romiſh Church, to be ordayned for a perpetuall rule of truth? and from whence haue ye drawen that to be true, which is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the greateſt number? Verely ye ſhall neuer proue this, out of the bookes of the old or new Teſtament. For thoſe corrupt argumentes: <hi>Vpon this rocke I haue builded my Church:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16.18. Luk. 22.23.</note> 
               <hi>I baue prayed for thee Peter that thy fayth faile not:</hi> and that ſaying of Chriſte thriſe repeated, <hi>feed my ſheepe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 21.15.16</note> with men not altogether ignorant of theſe thinges, need not any further confutation. But happely, ye will prooue it out of the writinges of auncient fathers. As though for ſooth it were the ſame thing, to commende the faith and religion of the church of <hi>Rome</hi> (as long as it was worthy praiſe) and to eſtabliſh hir for the catholicke church, or a perpetuall rule to the catholicke
<pb facs="tcp:1688:11"/> church. And ſeeing that by the name of the church of <hi>Rome</hi> (if theſe flatterers will ſpeake that they thinke) they doe vnderſtand no other thing, than the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> him ſelfe, what madneſſe is this, I beſeech you, to haue the deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſo great a controuerſie, to depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeat, in which their own writers being witnes, not ſo much the monſters of men, as Sathan himſelfe, doth ſeeme to haue ſit ſo many ages together.</p>
            <p>Theſe men replie, that the dignitie it <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſelfe, and the authoritie of the ſeate, is not taken away by the faults of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: euen as the Leuiticall high prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, was true then alſo, when it was exerciſed by vngracious and wicked high prieſtes. And neither do we thinke that either the dignitie, or els the effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the miniſterie, may be aboliſhed, thorowe the faultes of the miniſters (which thinge theſe men yet thinke when it pleſeth them, as they that hang that their tranſubſtantiation, vpon the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their ſacrificing prieſtes a very rotten coard ſurely) but this we ſay that (their principle being graunted, to wit,
<pb facs="tcp:1688:12"/> that the Byſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is that head, that ſhould ſtand the catholique church, as in ſtead of a ſoule) it muſt altogether followe, that this head be wyſe, if they will haue all his members, that is, the particular Churches to be wiſe: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if that be frantick, that the whole Churche muſt be franticke alſo. Now, that the Romiſh Biſhoppes haue beene franticke many ages together, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as priuate men, but ſpecially alſo as Biſhops: that is to ſay, that euerie one of them almoſt haue bene, not onely the moſt wicked of all men in reſpecte of their conuerſation, (which thing theſe men can not denie, vnleſſe they woulde rather be conuinced by their owne teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies:) but alſo as concerning the points of our religion, whilſt that, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they haue neglected all true religion, and partly alſo haue ſet them ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, ſo much that (which thing two or three ages ago <hi>Petrarcha</hi> hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, whoſe verſes they commend.) <hi>Rome</hi> hath beene a thouſande yeeres at the leaſt, the temple of hereſie, and hath vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ſubuerted (as much as was in hir)
<pb facs="tcp:1688:12"/> all the offices of Chriſt, yea ſo far forth that ſhee hath exalted hir ſelfe, aboue Chriſte him ſelfe (as the Apoſtles <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Paule,</hi> greater than all exception haue fore tolde: all the beſte approoued writers, Gréeke &amp; Latin, being the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of other churches, ſo interpreting the ſame) vnleſſe we haue ſufficiently heretofore proued it, we are ready again to prooue it, before all vpright iudges. Let this controuerſie therefore, be firſte decided, O yea Sophiſters, before that ye of this fained foundation, as it were, graunted vnto you.</p>
            <p>But go to, let vs graunt that the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes of <hi>Rome</hi> were ſuche, whoſe ſo great and large ſucceſſion is alleadged by theſe men. Who yet vnleſſe he be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly out of his wittes, will therefore conclude, that the biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> is the vniuerſall head, to whome who ſo euer doth cleaue, is to be iudged a true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Catholique Church? And yet theſe be the ſophiſtications of theſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fellowes, which will haue catholique and Roman to be one and the ſelfe ſame thing: to wit, becauſe <hi>Paule</hi> wrote, that
<pb facs="tcp:1688:13"/> 
               <hi>in his time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>the faith of the Romans, was famous throughout all the world.</hi> But how much more rightly nowe, may we ſay, that the ſtenche of that whore, hath not onely filled the earth, but hath aſcended alſo, euen to heauen: and that excellent epiſtle of the Apoſtle written to the olde <hi>Romans,</hi> ought now truely to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten againſte the <hi>Romans</hi> their ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Let vs now come vnto thoſe, who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme their catholicke churche,<note place="margin">The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church muſt not be eſteemed by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</note> by the number and glorious ſhew of pages or ſeriaunts. Verely if theſe men ſpeake truth, Chriſt and his flocke, ſhall iuſtly be pronounced excommunicat, and that multitude ſhal be the catholicke church, which ſo often times cried out, <hi>Take him away,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.23.</note> 
               <hi>take him away, crucifie him.</hi> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle alſo ſhall be found a lyar, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Corinthians: <hi>Brethren yee ſee your calling:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.26.</note> 
               <hi>that we are not many wiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſhe, not many mightie, not many noble:</hi> to be ſhorte, then theſe men ſhall be worthie, (whom to confute we may take paines) when either by reaſon or examples, they ſhall proue, that there
<pb facs="tcp:1688:13"/> are more wiſe men than fooles. Now then, I thinke it doth ſufficiently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that, by this bare ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which they brag of, that true catholike church, wherein we muſt abyde, cannot be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned from the falſe Churche, from which we ought of neceſſitie to depart.</p>
            <p>But yet, before that we conclude this place, we muſte refell an argument, which theſe Sophiſters would haue to be deemed ſuch a one as cannot be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. For ſay they,<note place="margin">Hovv the fathers vſed the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of perſonall ſucceſſion.</note> the fathers ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, from the ſucceſſion of biſhoppes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt auncient heretiques. But againe what can be more corrupt than this ſubtle kind of reaſoning? for this is that which is well knowne, euen to children which they are wount to call an elench,<note n="[a]" place="margin">The fallacie of compoſition or diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is a falſe concluſion, made by a wrong application of wordes alleadged or ſpoken: referring that to one, which is alleadged, or ſpoken to an other.</note> or a fallacy of compoſition and diuyſion. Firſt therfore I deny, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the auncient fathers, were myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to vſe the recitall of Biſhops, but to haue recourſe rather euen to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. And why ſo? that the authoritie of
<pb facs="tcp:1688:14"/> doctrine, rather than of perſons ſhoulde be mainteined? But theſe men obiect vnto vs, the ſucceſſion of their biſhops, not in déede biſhops, ſo far letting paſſe the mention of that Apoſtolicall doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, that they woulde haue it accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a wicked thing, to demaund it at his handes, that woulde proue him ſelfe to ſucceed the auncient byſhoppes. Now I pray you, howe many authors of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, haue ſit in thoſe chiefe ſeates of <hi>Alexandria, Antioche, Constantinople?</hi> yea, what ſeat will theſe men ſhew me ſomewhat more famous, where ſome hereticall biſhops, haue not helde their ſeate? And as touching the <hi>Romiſh</hi> chayre, from which theſe men by a rotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coard hang the catholique church. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norius</hi> the<note n="[a]" place="margin">Monothelites, were certain heretiks about the yeare. 565, who affirmed that there vvas but one will and one action in Chriſt: denying that ther was in him two naturall willes and actions, which might aunſvvere to his two natures.</note> 
               <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nothelite,</hi> openly condemned of the ſixt general coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell and priuate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Agatho</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhoppe: And <hi>Iohn</hi> the 22. thinking euill touching the ſoule of man: in like manner condemned of the
<pb facs="tcp:1688:14"/> colledge of <hi>Sorbon</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> were ſounde to haue ſit in that ſeate. To let paſſe,<note n="[a]" place="margin">Liberius for ambitions ſake fell into the Arrian hereſie.</note> 
               <hi>Liberius,</hi>
               <note n="[b]" place="margin">He, while Siluerius the Pope liued (by the ayde of Beliſarius, the captaine of the Emperors armie, obteined the popedome.</note> 
               <hi>Vigilius,</hi> and<note n="[c]" place="margin">He meaneth of Anaſtaſius the 2. who fell into the hereſie of Arrius and Eutiches, which hereſies Acatius alſo him ſelfe did propound, about the yeere, 484.</note> 
               <hi>Anasta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> whom I ſee of ſome to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, although <hi>Gratian.</hi> 2. <hi>Disti.</hi> 19. reckeneth this laſt alſo as an <hi>Acatian</hi> heretique a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the condemned Popes.</p>
            <p>But if any man would obiect, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe are blotted out of the number of By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and therfore are not comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in that title or role of ſucceſſion: yet this he ſhal be inforced to graunt vs, to wit, that the ſucceſſion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeat of <hi>Rome,</hi> was then at the leaſt broken of, when theſe were therefore blotted out (which perſons notwithſtanding they themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues as yet number in their Catologue) becauſe they had declined from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall doctrine. Whervpon followeth that which <hi>Tertulian</hi> rightly affirmeth that religion ought to be proued or tried not by the perſons,<note place="margin">Tertulian.</note> but the perſons by re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligion.
<pb facs="tcp:1688:15"/> But here truly I confeſſe, that I do ſomwhat ouerſhoot my ſelf, for ſeeing the queſtion is of doctrine, what doth this appertaine, to the Byſhops of the Churche of <hi>Rome,</hi> whome all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome knoweth nowe ſo manye yeeres, to haue beene for nothing leſſe carefull, then for anye doctrine, eyther true or falſe, but onely for to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhe and enlarge theire owne ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie.</p>
            <p>But they will ſay, no man hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned theſe Popes. I confes it. For who would haue taken to himſelf this law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful authority againſt their tiranny, who had perſwaded all men, that they ought to be iudged of none? Therefore there hath bene not of late onely, but many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges together, not an interruption, but a full abruption or renting of the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Rome,</hi> from the body of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique true church, except peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture theſe men iudge, that it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe, eyther to belleeue nothing, or to teache nothing, than to be an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique.</p>
            <p>And I beſéeche you what impudencie
<pb facs="tcp:1688:15"/> is this,<note place="margin">True doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine ought to go before true ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> to haue the knowledge of trueth to hang vpon ſucceſſion? wheras on the contrary, theſe men themſelues can not deny, but that the trueth ought neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to go before ſucceſſion.</p>
            <p>And theſe Sophiſters,<note place="margin">The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian church in the time of Chriſte, coulde not be knovvne by the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Perſons.</note> if they had bene in the times of Chriſt, by what Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſucceſſion, would they haue acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the true church? ſurely not by the title or name of the Leuiticall high prieſts? becauſe that prieſthood was then at an end: and Chriſt cannot be called the ſucceſſour of <hi>Aaron</hi> vnleſſe <hi>Iudaiſme</hi> be agayne eſtabliſhed: wherefore alſo <hi>he is ſayd to be made a high priest,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.16.17</note> 
               <hi>not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the order of Leui, but according to the order of Melchiſedec,</hi> Therefore the holy men at that time, acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Catholique church, without the marke of perſonall ſucceſſion: to wit, by the compariſon of the doctrine of the Prophetes, with the doctrine of Chriſte him ſelfe, and the Apoſtles. Which is ſo farre true, that on the contrarye, none haue leſſe acknowledged Chriſte, than they that haue cleaued to a Byſhoply ſucceſſion. Therefore that perſonall
<pb facs="tcp:1688:16"/> ſucceſſion, is no true and perpetuall marke of the Catholique Church.</p>
            <p>Theſe men happely, beeing driuen from the Leuiticall ſucceſſion, will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine obiect another ſucceſſion from the Prophetes. But neyther ſo, ſhall they ſpeake the truth, if they ſticke in the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons them ſelues, for the ſucceſſion of Prophetes was not perpetuall, no more than the ſucceſſion of Prieſts: yea rather it was broken of a long time, eſpecially after <hi>Malachie.</hi> They wil alſo obiect vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs that ſaying:<note place="margin">Mat. 23.2.</note> 
               <hi>The Scribes &amp; Phariſes ſit in Moſes chaire.</hi> But agayne, they ſhold remember, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Chriſt to haue ſaid: <hi>Take heed of the leauen of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16.6.</note> And therefore by that ſaying of Chriſt, we are not called backe to a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of perſons, but to a ſucceſſion of doctrine.</p>
            <p>But I haue beſides an other thing more peremptorye (as they them ſelues ſpeake) to aunſwere againſte that, in which theſe men falſly boaſt themſelues to followe the authoritie of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in diſcrying the church, by which thing alſo their wilines may more and
<pb facs="tcp:1688:16"/> more be made manifeſt. I denie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">The aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fathers vſed not the argument of perſonall ſucceſſion againſt all heretiques.</note> that any of the auncient fathers haue at any time made mention of this ſucceſſion, but either againſt Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, whileſt yet a lawfull ſucceſſion remayned, (as it was done againſt the <hi>Donatistes</hi>) or againſte them, whiche brought forth new bookes of our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as were, in the beginning almoſt an infinite nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as<note n="[a]" place="margin">I ſuppoſe that he ſpeketh here of Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus, mentioned in Act. 8. of whom many thinges are writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the old writers, ſpecially he affirmed that Chriſte was not come, neither ſuffered any thing of the Iewes, but that he himſelf was Chriſt</note> 
               <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
               <note n="[b]" place="margin">He amongſt other things taught, that Chriſt the ſonne of God, tooke not mans fleſh of the virgin, but that he had a ſpirituall or heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which paſſed thorow the virgin Marie, as wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thorovv a pipe or Conduit. He vvas about the yeere. 150.</note> 
               <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentine,</hi>
               <note n="[c]" place="margin">He affirmed, that Chriſt appeared not in the ſubſtance of fleſh, but in a phantaſticall body, &amp; that one Simon vvas crucified in his ſteede, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yeare. 124.</note> 
               <hi>Baſilides,</hi>
               <note n="[d]" place="margin">He taught that Chriſte vvas not very man, and that he aſcended into heauen vvithout his fleſh, and firſt made lavves for abſtinence from meates and marriages, hee vvas in the yeare. 180.</note> 
               <hi>Montane,</hi> to conclude y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole troup of moſt ſhameleſſe men. After this ſort the Fathers of right iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and reſerued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe
<pb facs="tcp:1688:17"/>
               <note place="margin">Such as pretended to be inſpired vvith reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The Meſſalian he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques vvere ſo called, who affirmed that bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme and the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per did neither profit nor hurt, but that thoſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che gaue themſelues to prayer onely or ſleeping ſhould be inſpired vvith the ſpirite, vvhich being once receyued, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards they had no need of the word, or any other exerciſe of godlines, but that he that vvas ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, vvas altogether vvithout ſinne, and did foreſee thinges to come, and did ſometimes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold God with their eies.</note> 
               <hi>Enthuſiasts,</hi> ſaying. If your doctrine be true, eyther there hath not beene euer yet anye churche, or the doctrine which you alleage is old and ancient. But that both theſe thinges are falſe, appeareth by that, both becauſe the apoſtles haue gathered together the churche of Chriſte, and you teach your doctrines, as taken not out of the writings of the Apoſtles, but as newely reuealed vnto you by the holy ghoſt. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, (ſayd the fathers,) both theſe things appeare by that, that we count the beginnings of our churches, by aſcending vpward, euen to the Apoſtles themſelues: but you could not haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from the Apoſtles your thinges, which ye firſt deuiſed.</p>
            <p>Here remained one thing, which the moſte ſubtile of thoſe moſte fantaſticall perſons obiected, to wit, that all things were not reuealed to the apoſtles, and therfore that men ought to beleeue their
<pb facs="tcp:1688:17"/> reuelations alſo. But <hi>Tertulian</hi> (whom I maruail, could afterward be deceiued w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> 
               <hi>Montanus</hi> holy ghoſte) moſt plentifully, and ſtrongly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futeth this preſcription, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Lord hath neither kept backe any thing from the apoſtles, (the chiefe builders of his church:) nor agayn, that the apoſtles haue concealed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe things, which they had receiued of Chriſte. After this ſort I ſay, the fathers v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the argument of the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of perſons agaynſte thoſe heretiques, altogether by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration as it were. But they vſed it not in like ſorte, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <note n="[a]" place="margin">So called of Paulus Samoſatenus, vvho de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the ſonne of God, to haue deſcended from heauén, but that Chriſt did proceed from Marie in the earth, hee was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yeare, 372.</note> 
               <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moſatans</hi>
               <note n="[b]" place="margin">So called of one Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellius, who taught that there was but onely one perſon in the godhead, &amp; confeſſed that the trinity was diſtincted in reſpect of names only, &amp; not in reſpecte of perſons. He was about the yeare 320.</note> 
               <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellians,</hi>
               <note n="[c]" place="margin">So called of one Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rius, who affirmed, that the Son was not truly &amp; naturally God, neither coeternall with the father, but to haue had a beginning, &amp; to be made of nothing, he was about the yere, 320</note> 
               <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi>
               <note n="[d]" place="margin">So called of one Pellagius, who held free will, and that euery man might obtayne ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation by his owne workes: that infants were borne, vvithout originall ſin: and that Adam hurt himſelfe onely by his fall. He vvas about the yeare, 466.</note> 
               <hi>Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans:</hi> to be ſhort, againſte anye with whome, the queſtyon was not of the very bookes, but of the
<pb facs="tcp:1688:18"/> meaning, becauſe this had beene verie fooliſhe.</p>
            <p>Briefly therfore I anſwere theſe two thinges: that the auncient Fathers, whoſe authoritie theſe men ſhameleſlie abuſe, haue, neither at any time ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſucceſſion of their biſhops, from the ſucceſſion of the Apoſtolical doctrine: nor haue ſet this ſucceſſion, againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other heretiques, but againſt thoſe, of whom ſome new reuelation was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended: As at this day of the<note n="[a]" place="margin">They mayntaine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt other errors, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelations, and take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay the baptiſme of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants.</note> 
               <hi>Anabaptistes,</hi>
               <note n="[b]" place="margin">They (caſting a ſide all feare of God vvhat ſo euer) hold, that men may lyue as they liſt.</note> 
               <hi>Libertines</hi>
               <note n="[c]" place="margin">So called of one Caſper Svvingfeldius, vvho held, the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes do.</note> 
               <hi>Swingfeldians.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for as muche as now the controuerſie is, betwixt the <hi>Romanistes</hi> and vs, for two thinges onely, to wit, for the interpretation of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and whether the wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges of the Prophetes and Apoſtles, doe moſt fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, what ſo euer we ought to beleeue, it is prooued that they, in the firſt point, impudently abuſe the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the fathers, in alleadging againſt vs the argument of ſucceſſion: and in
<pb facs="tcp:1688:18"/> the other, is miniſtred vnto vs a ſure weapon, to confute them. And that this ſucceſſion alſo was alleadged againſt the <hi>Donatistes</hi> as <hi>Schiſmatickes,</hi> this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing toucheth vs, whom theſe men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, not properly for <hi>Sciſmatickes,</hi> but for heretiques: of which thing notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, we will ſay ſome thing in his proper place.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">That the falſe church of Rome, is not onely not propped vp, by the argument deriued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the perſonal ſucceſſion of the apoſtles: but alſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrown, although the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be not of the doctrine</note>But go to, let vs gratify them a litle. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and (which thing may be done without any preiudice of the trueth). Let vs graunt vnto theſe men how much force ſoeuer they can imagine, of that their perſonall ſucceſſion. What ſhall this I beſech you, help their cauſe?</p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">That there vvas neuer any Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall, vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall head, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that his ſucceſſion is not Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall.</note>For, that we may begin, at the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſtep of their <hi>Hierarchie,</hi> or prieſtlike gouernement, as they call it, that is, at that vniuerſall myniſteriall head (vnto whome they afterwarde, appropriated the name of Pope, which before was common to all Biſhoppes,) they ſhal as eaſely finde the Diuell him ſelfe in the kingdome of God, as any ſuch head, either in the bookes of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or in the auncient church. For ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="tcp:1688:19"/> children know this, how falſe, foliſh, and abſurd arguments they be, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they bring out of the ſcriptures to proue the ſame. And as concerning the hiſtory of that auncient purer church: (that is to ſay, in this behalfe verelie, euen to the tymes of that manſlaier <hi>Phocas</hi>) they ſhall finde none, that ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted the primacies, and glorious titles, which are attributed to the biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> (although in deed the biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> ambitiouſlie ſought nothing more, and there wanted not ſome, who moſt ſhamleſly euen then flattered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) as that they did for all that, gyue this degree of vniuerſall head vnto him. Therfore, they haue not Chriſt, nor <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> but that moſt vile man of al, <hi>Phocas</hi> I ſay, the emperor, for the author of this vniuerſallitie: and they haue <hi>Boniface</hi> the thirde, the head or beginner of this tyrannie: or (that I may vſe the words of <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great himſelfe) the chiefe or head of <hi>Antichristianiſme:</hi> in ſo much, that the Romiſhe popedome, doth but onely ſixtene yeares at the moſt, goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Mahumetiſme,</hi> or the turkiſhe reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1688:19"/>
            <p>But, by what ſleightes, that monſter hath vſurped, and attayned this tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, who, I praie you, at this day can be ignorant, vnleſſe he be ignorant of hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, or whoſe eyes Satan hath blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? yea, ſeeing that this moſt holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, doth boaſt him ſelfe to be, not the ſucceſſor of <hi>Peter</hi> alone, but of <hi>Paul</hi> alſo (whoſe heads being cut off, not ſo much by newes hang men, as by the Pope himſelfe, he ingraueth in theſe his lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſeales): it muſt needs be, either that afterward two heads were growen into one, whoſe authoritie afterward, paſſed for ſooth to this ſucceſſor of them both: or els that neither <hi>Peter</hi> nor <hi>Paule,</hi> were this onely vniuerſal, miniſteriall head: except he woulde rather acknowledge, that the catholique churche, hath had at the beginning two heades vppon the earth.</p>
            <p>But what ſay I? that I may ſpeake nothing here of ſo many <hi>Antipopes,</hi> or Popes one againſt an other, when as <hi>Liberius</hi> and <hi>Damaſus,</hi> at one and the ſame time, (as all men affirme), obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:1688:20"/> that ſeate of <hi>Rome,</hi> where was then that one vniuerſall head? And let theſe thinges be ſufficiently ſpoken, touching the deliuerie of that ſpirituall ſworde from hand to hand.</p>
            <p>And as concerning that other ſworde, which they call, ſecular or politique, wherewith they haue ouerthrowen all magiſtracie: From whence I pray you do they take the beginning of this iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction? for, though we ſhoulde beleeue that fable, of the donation or gyfte of <hi>Constantine,</hi> to be as true, as it was ſhameleſly fayned, yet truely it ſhal not be ſet from the apoſtles, but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror: neither yet graunted by Chriſt, or by <hi>Peter,</hi> but by men. Which thing not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, was neyther lawfull for <hi>Constantine</hi> to do, nor for the Biſhoppe of <hi>Rome</hi> to receaue, although it had beene willingly offered him. Wherefore, if they ſhall of their owne authoritie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre agayne theſe two feathers, the churche thoſe former, to wit, the eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall gouernement, and Kinges and Princes theſe latter, to wit, ciuill iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and authoritie (both which in
<pb facs="tcp:1688:20"/> their time ſhall come to paſſe) this fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low will then appeare, not the head of the church, but an vnfeathered cuckow. And theſe things concerning this head, haue I put down in few words, becauſe they haue of late, by them of our ſide ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie plentifully, both out of the worde of God, &amp; out of the trueſt hiſtories of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, &amp; to be ſhort, out of the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, ben mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly declared and plentifully proued.</p>
            <p>Now the head of this ſucceſſion being cut off,<note place="margin">That there can be noe Apoſtolicall ſucceſſion in the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalles, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trapolitanes, Primates, or Archbiſhops</note> what ſhall the reſt of the body be, but a roteen and ſtinking carkas? Truely them ſelues are compelled to confeſſe, that the next degree vnto this head, to wit, the order of cardinalles, as it is nowe, cannot be ſet from the more auncient time. There follow primates and Archbiſhoppes, for ſcarce the verie name of Patriarkſhippe, is yet remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and <hi>Mahomet,</hi> at the length hath ended the matter incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, which firſte aroſe, betweene the<note n="[a]" place="margin">That is, thoſe foure men that tooke vppon them, the gouernment of the vvhol world he meaneth the foure Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to wit, Hieruſalem, Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria, Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople &amp; Rome.</note> 
               <hi>Quartumvi. i,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards betweene the
<pb facs="tcp:1688:21"/>
               <note n="[a]" place="margin">That is the fiue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that toke vppon them the gouernement of the world.</note> 
               <hi>Quintumuiri.</hi> Therefore the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi> councell it ſelfe, doth not refer the beginning of theſe offices, to the word of God, or Apoſtolicall inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, eyther written, or not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, but to ancient cuſtome. So that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can this ſucceſſion, be thought to be Apoſtolicall.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The degree of Biſhopps wherin they are exalted a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boue the reſt of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, was vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knowen to the Apoſtles and therfore that there is no Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion therof.</note>There reſt yet Biſhoppes ſo called of them, to wit, which are ſet in euerie dioceſſe aboue miniſters (for the other inferiour orders, theſe pleaders of ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion, nothing eſteeme,) whoſe onely ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion neuertheleſſe, hath ſome ſhew of Apoſtolicall ſucceſſion. But it maye plainely apeare, out of the firſte Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinth:</hi> not onely that there was no ſuche degree of Biſhops ordeyned by the Apoſtles, as immediatly afterward was brought into the Church, after the times of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles: neither y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther was any ſuch allowed of the Apoſtle, to wit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther ſhould be one degree of a biſhop, and an other of a miniſter, or that ſome man ſhould be called a Biſhoppe, not in reſpect of a flock, but in reſpect of his fel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low elders. For who doubteth, but that
<pb facs="tcp:1688:21"/> the Apoſtle, woulde haue gyuen this counſel vnto the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> or himſelfe woulde haue perfourmed it, or haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed it to <hi>Caephas</hi> or <hi>Apollo,</hi> if (which thing <hi>Hierome</hi> hath written to <hi>Euagrius,</hi> and in his commentaries vpon the firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Titus</hi>) he had iudged this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie profitable, much more neceſſarie, for the brydling of <hi>Schiſmes?</hi> But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were lawfull, to ordayne this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in the Church, or not (for of this I like not nowe to diſpute) that thing is not only apparant out of <hi>Hierom,</hi> vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> epiſtle to <hi>Titus,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Biſhops are greater than miniſters, rather by cuſtome, than by the truth of the Lords appoyntment: But alſo by witneſſes which theſe men (as greater than all exception), are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to alleadge, as <hi>Lucius</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope, <hi>Clement</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Anacletus</hi> (vnleſſe their Epiſtles be rather counterfaite, which yet theſe men cite for authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call.) <hi>Lombard</hi> in his fourth booke of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences the 24. <hi>distinct: Gratian,</hi> and to be ſhort <hi>Cardinall Cuſan,</hi> in his booke of the vniuerſall vnitie, &amp; <hi>Platina,</hi> in the life of Pope <hi>Bonifacius</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third: al which plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:1688:22"/> witneſſe, that all this <hi>Hierarchicall</hi> or prieſtlike gouernment aboue miniſters was deuiſed by men, after the example of the <hi>Roman</hi> empyre, that is to ſay, that it is the true <hi>Imag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the beast, deſcribed in the reuelalion of Iohn.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 13.1. Reuel, 14.9.</note> For whoſe cauſe ſome, in the beginning alſo did trauaile which ment not to performe that which afterward inſued. The thing it ſelfe in fine, taught vs, that it was a matter of great importance to decline, euen but a nailes bredth from the word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the diſputation, touching the ſucceſſion of perſons, ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from the ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</note>Now, for as much as theſe thinges be ſo, that is, ſeeing neither this ſucceſſion of perſons, is a ſufficient, true and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per marke of the Churche, nor (though we ſhould graunt it ſuch) pertayneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing at all, to this popiſhe vizard. What is then the matter, wherein we ſee ſome at this day ſo greatly to ſticke, that no ſmall number (as though<note n="[a]" place="margin">That is ſome fearefull &amp; terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing.</note> 
               <hi>Gorgons</hi> head were caſte in the way), goe backe? Verely this is the ſtrength of the ſpirite of error, that they which are prooued and pure, may be made manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Now let vs heare alſo, ſuche an other
<pb facs="tcp:1688:22"/> teſtimonie of their impudencie:<note place="margin">That the ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nonicall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyning of Miniſters, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary mark of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church.</note> they wil haue that to be iudged a Church, where there continueth an ordinary calling, to the holy miniſterie. But what other thing is this, than (after the example of that hoſtiſe of <hi>Chalcis</hi>) to ſet before vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the ſame meate new dreſt? Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, becauſe here againe, I ſée ſome ſticke as it were at a rocke, and that, not without danger of ſhipwrack: I will indeuour and that as it were by the wind of truth, hence to deliuer them, that are caſt vpon this coaſt.</p>
            <p>Truely,<note place="margin">Paſtors muſt in deede, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be ſent by the Lorde, but there is not alwayes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like order of their ſending</note> if a man bid them declare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, what they vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, by the name of ordination, (which requeſte in this queſtion, is altogether honeſt and verie neceſſarie) then the clawes of theſe Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wil openly ſhew themſelues. They will alleadge, that of the Apoſtle: <hi>How ſhall they preache vnleſſe they be ſent:</hi> and that ſaying:<note place="margin">Rom. 10.15. 1. Cor. 14.40</note> 
               <hi>All things ought to be done in the houſe of God, rightly and in order.</hi> We agrée vnto it. They will ſay, that, all that order is comprehended, in the olde <hi>Canons,</hi> which may not or ought not, by any meanes be broken.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1688:23"/>
            <p>Firſt, we aunſwere, that it is playne, by the compariſon of the very <hi>Canons,</hi> that one, and the ſame order in the Chriſtian Churches, neither alwayes hath beene preſcribed, nor euerie where kept: and that alſo, the diuerſitie of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, cannot ſuffer this, that one order in theſe thinges, ſhoulde be euerie where, and alwayes exactly obſerued: and therefore very vnſeaſonablie, is the obſeruation, euen of the moſte auncient and beſt <hi>Canons</hi> required, as abſolutely and neceſſarilie to be kept. And if they be here ſo impudent, that they will deny this thing, truely I will conuince them as manifeſt offenders. For, if it be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull,<note place="margin">Although the canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed for a perpetuall marke of the catholique church, yet it reproueth the falſe church of Rome.</note> to omit any thing of the <hi>Canons</hi> without any exception? From whence commeth that greate gaine, vnto the court of <hi>Rome,</hi> by diſpenſation alſo euen with the law of God? neither truely wil I eaſely ſuffer my ſelf, to be thruſt from this exception.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="sup">a</hi> But go to, we are content here to do theſe men a pleaſure, let vs therfore ſay (the diſputation of this exception beyng deferred) that vocation is an order, not
<pb facs="tcp:1688:23"/> onely agreable to the worde of God, but alſo euen to the verie auncient pure <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons,</hi> by which an eccleſiaſticall office, is committed to ſome man. Let vs graunt them alſo (yet with no preiudice of the truth) that there alſo the true Church is to be ſeene, where this order continueth ſound and pure, yet I ſay, that by that meanes, it moſt certainely appeareth that that Popiſhe Churche is, nothing leſſe than that catholique church, whoſe name it chalengeth to hir ſelfe? For tell me, what is this order? to wit, that a lawfull knowledge of learning, and of manners going before, and the order of eccleſiaſticall degrees beeing not raſhly violated: ſome man (by the free conſent of any whole Church, touching which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> queſtion is) being appointed to this holy miniſterie, is ordained by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of whom he ought, that is, is put into the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as it were of his office. And if anie man breake this order, that is, if a fault happen, either in the examination, or in the election, all the pure <hi>Canons</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, all that, to be iudged of no ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: and ſo they ſubiect him, that orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:1688:24"/> the miniſter, to moſte gréeuous puniſhmentes. That this is ſo, they them ſelues cannot denie. Wherefore I woulde not load many leaues, with the alleadging of <hi>Canons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let theſe men come forth, and let them alleadge vnto vs, euen one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all their clergie, in whome this order, hath beene thorowly obſerued. I demaund not, whether theſe thinges, preſcribed both by the word of God, and alſo by the pure <hi>Canons,</hi> haue bene exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerued of them now a long time. But this I aſke, whether there be any vſe of election, amongeſt them in the moſt places, ſeeing that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romiſh har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, hath couenaunted with Kings &amp; Princes, for the aboliſhment of it, and ſuffereth thoſe bargaines to be printed, and ſet out to ſale. Now where there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth any ſhew of election, woulde a man haue thought any of them, coulde haue beene ſo impudent, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhoulde be ſo bold, as to denie, that thoſe offices which the whole world knoweth, are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly gotten by purchaſe: and that by buying free voyces (which thing is ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb facs="tcp:1688:24"/> practiſed, amongſt them that ſeke for prieſthood, and Canonicall perſons (as they call them, that is to ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſwine and aſſes, which are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vncleane beaſtes) to be ſo bold I ſaye, as to denie it, to be anye other thing, than an abhominable treading vnder foote of all law, both Gods owne, and of that purer part of the canon law (as they call it)? And of the triall, both of doctrine and maners, the lawful wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, for ſooth, be thoſe wicked men, getting their liuing by no other means but by dayly and open periuries, partly in the prouinces of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> partly, in the lappe of that Romiſh har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotte. And this thing for ſooth the high Biſhops know not, which begin their bulles with theſe wordes. <hi>The honestie of life and maners, vppon which commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſame vnto vs, by a credible ttstimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, &amp;c.</hi> What ſay I? their lawes of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, either ordinarie, or falling out vpon ſome (as they call them): and the lawes of reſignation, where were they deuiſed, braied, ſtrained out, &amp; at length, ſet out and deliuered, to make mad, all
<pb facs="tcp:1688:25"/> both the higheſt and the loweſt, but in the deuilles kitchin? And yet theſe men for ſooth, will prooue the Eccleſiaſticall calling, to remaine in their poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">That the falſe clergie of Rome doth raſhly diſpute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, for the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands.</note>But againe let vs heare that, that may more conuince theſe mens ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe. When they diſpute with vs of a calling they are wont to vrge the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands, as though the true dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of a lawfull and counterfaite calling conſiſted in that. But I ſuppoſe, theſe good men haue not forgotten, that, which I euen now ſaide, to wit, that by al the old canons, his ordination ſhould be iudged of no force, who hath not bene lawfully examined and choſen,<note place="margin">That no Paſtors are ordeyned by the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of handes, but being alredy ordeined, are put into the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their office and commended vnto God.</note> and they that ordeyne ſuche, to be ſubiect alſo to very gréeuous puniſhment. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they doe vainely challenge vnto them ſelues that, which is no where found amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Moreouer this alſo they ſhould know, that Paſtours, are not made by the lay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing on of hands, but being ordeined by a lawfull calling (which is the voyce of God) are ſo commended, and put into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poſſeſſion of the miniſtery. For, wheras
<pb facs="tcp:1688:25"/> they recken, this ceremony of laying on of handes, amongſt ſacramentes, by the ſame reaſon that they recken baptiſme, and the ſupper of the Lord: we ſay, that it is altogether a vaine dotage, ſeeing there is no expreſſe commaundement of that ceremonie extant, neither is there ioyned vnto it, any ſacramentall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, neyther doe we reiect, eyther this ceremony, or iudge to bee vnprofitable the prayers of the church, commending and as it were, offering vnto God, the Paſtor that hee hath ſent them, for the ſending of God, is a lawful calling. But here ſurely, it falleth out with theſe hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, as it hath in other things alſo, to wit, that thoſe things being omitted, in which a true calling conſiſteth (that is to ſay the trial of doctrine, and of life, and a lawfull election of the whole Church) they ſticke in the outward ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie, whiche ceremonie alſo they haue defiled, with infinit vicelike rites: that I may let paſſe, that horrible ſale of benefices and treading vnderfoote of the old cannons, made, touching the multiplication of benefices (as they call
<pb facs="tcp:1688:26"/> them) and touching ordination, by ouer leaping (as they ſpeake of inferior or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.) And yet notwithſtanding, they themſelues are not ignorant, that, by the ful conſent of the ancient Synodes, not onely ordination, but alſo, other bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter parts of a calling, are, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes, iudged of no force.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">That euen a lawfull ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, is not a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together a neceſſarye marke of the true church, eyther Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique or particular.</note>But goe too, let vs put the cafe alſo, that all theſe men, were both lawfullye choſen and ordeined. Shal therfore their congregation be the catholique church, or not rather a denne of théeues, if in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing their calling, they turne lighte into darkeneſſe, and perfourme this one thing alone, to make ſlaues to Sathan, the ſheepe, that ſhoulde bee brought to Chriſte? And yet if forſooth, the head of his falſe Church doe this (as what els I pray you doth he?) he will not endure this, that he may be iudged of any mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man. For ſo theſe men haue beene bolde, nowe a long time, not onely to ſpeake, but alſo to write. And if this bee playnely to play the <hi>Antichrist:</hi> what is this Catholique Church (I beſeech you) of which <hi>Antichrist</hi> is the head?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1688:26"/>
            <p>Wherefore,<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the whole former diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, of the perſonal ſucceſſion &amp; ordination.</note> (that I may at the length conclude this place) I ſuppoſe, that theſe two thinges, doe nowe ſufficiently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that neither a baſe ſucceſſion of perſons, nor the obſeruation of an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde vocation, is that neceſſarye, and perpetuall marke, of the true Churche, which the Logitians call proper after the<note n="[a]" place="margin">That is, whiche agreeth to euery one of the kind, onely to the kind, and always to the kinde: as to be apt to laugh, agreeth to all men, to men only, and alwaies to them, and to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye particuler of that kinde.</note> fourth ſort. Neither al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it ſhoulde be ſo, doe theſe things at any thing at al, belong to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> (ſuch as now it is) that is vnto the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: but rather what argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſoeuer conuince the Churche of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> the ſame doe ſo eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeare in this Harlot, that, he that would not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, flye from, and deteſt her, as an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultreſſe forſaken of her huſbande, true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye,<note place="margin">A true defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of the true church, and a proper, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and perpetuall marke of the ſame.</note> muſt either nothing regarde theſe things or elſe be without all vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>Nowe, becauſe we haue determined, not onely to ſet out the falſe markes, (which thinges wee ſuppoſe wee haue done?) but alſo, to poynte out as it were
<pb facs="tcp:1688:27"/> with the finger, the true and proper markes of the Church. Go to let vs at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt this latter point. We ſay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that a true definition of a true Church, eyther particularly, or vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally conſidered, is that, by which it is ſaid to be a congregation, that confeſſeth the true Ieſus Chriſte: their onely ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. For we ſay, that Ieſus Chriſte, is that onely foundation, of that true ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall houſe of God: Ieſus Chriſt onely, is the ſoule of that miſticall bodie: Ieſus Chriſte onely, is the ſquare of that buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The true Chriſte muſt be diſcerned from the falſe, by the onely wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges of the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles.</note>The aduerſaries will aunſwere, that they alſo acknowledge, and preache the ſame thing. Therefore we do adde (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there be many falſe Chriſtes) that we diſpute of the true Chriſte. Theſe men alſo will replie, that they haue done, and do the ſame. In the third place therefore we adde, that he is in deed the true Chriſt, that hath moſt fully reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him ſelfe, by the mouth of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles. And the mouth of the Prophetes and Apoſtles, we inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret to be, their authenticall writings,
<pb facs="tcp:1688:27"/> wherin we affirme, are moſt fully, and moſte perfectly comprehended all the pointes of the Chriſtian faith, partly plainely, and partly by neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences to be gathered thereof.</p>
            <p>For, we beléeue it, to be as abſurd,<note place="margin">that the true Chriſt muſt therefore be perfectly knowne by the writings of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did fully and plainly, both knovv and teach the whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes and Apoſtles, do yet in their writinges teach it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</note> to thinke, that the Apoſtles were igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of ſome thing, of the miſteries of chriſtianitie, or not to haue reuealed all thinges vnto the worlde (both which <hi>Tertulian</hi> hath iuſtly accounted, verie greate pointes of madneſſe): as not to haue put in writing, all things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to ſaluation: or, to be ſhort, not ſo to haue put them downe, that, either they ſhould not be plaine inough of them ſelues, or, if any thing be written ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more obſcure, their true interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ſhoulde be els where ſought, than out of their very writings. But here we haue the aduerſaries manifeſtly diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing from vs, yet not al, neither thoſe which like ſhameleſneſſe. For there be that graunt both theſe thinges, that is to ſay, that the Apoſtles knew perfectly all the doctrine of ſaluation, and taught all the ſame moſt faithfully vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:1688:28"/> Church: which thing in deed they iuſtly graunt, for as much as Chriſt him ſelfe, in the 15. of <hi>Iohn</hi> and the 16.13. witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this in moſt plaine wordes: And <hi>Paule</hi> in the 21.27. of the <hi>Actes. Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> 1.8. <hi>Hehrews.</hi> 1.1. otherwiſe it ſhold be falſe, at leaſt in ſome part, which the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaketh: to wit, <hi>That the Church is builded vppon the foundation of the Prophetes and Apostles:</hi> And that, which he witneſſeth of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. 2. <hi>Timot.</hi> 3.16.17. Moreouer, that ſhall be falſe to, which the ſame Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>That the Churche, is the piller of truth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.15.</note> Vnleſſe all truth beeing ingrauen in that piller ſhould be manifeſt. Other ſome, more ſhameleſſe, ſuppoſe there is left vnto theſe men, whom they call the ſucceſſours of the Apoſtles, I know not what excellent thing, and that they doe affirme ſo aſſuredly, that they hold, they can not be deceiued in that matter, whoſe opinion I ſuppoſe, néedeth not at this time, amongſt men of ſound iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, any confutation.</p>
            <p>But, in the ouerthrow of theſe two latter, and eſpecially of the laſt point, I
<pb facs="tcp:1688:28"/> perceiue, that all theſe men,<note place="margin">VVhat we ought to think of the vnwritten word.</note> are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of one opinion againſt vs. For they vrge, I knowe not what vnwritten worde, which they call Apoſtolicall tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. And verely I do not vnwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie graunt vnto them, that all thinges were not ſeuerally put downe in wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, according to the circumſtances of times, place and perſons, which were obſerued, either by the Apoſtles, or by their conſent, in the very forme and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the ſeruice of God.</p>
            <p>But who wil graunt, that we muſt thinke the ſame, of the decrees of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie doctrine it ſelfe? Finally, when the aduerſaries are bidden to bring forth, what theſe pointes be, then that lying ſpirit bewraieth himſelfe, becauſe thoſe thinges, which they will haue deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from hand to hand, could neither by word nor writinges, haue bene deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Apoſtles, but they ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from themſelues. But euen al the fathers of ſound iudgement, haue iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged farre other wiſe, of the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and moſte ſound perfection of the holy ſcriptures, with whoſe teſtimonies
<pb facs="tcp:1688:29"/> being a thouſand times alleadged, I thought it not good now to fill theſe leaues.</p>
            <p>There remayneth the queſtion to be handled,<note place="margin">The inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the vvritten vvord, is not elſe vvhere to be fet, then from the vvorde it ſelfe, to wit, by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the places one vvith ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and out of the ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie or pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portion of the articles of our fayth.</note> touching the interpretation of the ſcripture. Which truely is ſo toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to and fro by theſe men, that they cannot eſchew the ſinne of blaſphemie. There be I confeſſe ſome places of the ſcripture (partly through the ignorance of tongs, partly alſo, throgh other faults of our owne) ſo dark vnto vs, euen vntil this day, that as yet euen the moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned interpreters, and ſuch as be of beſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, cannot thoroughly agrée what ſhould be the proper &amp; natural meaning thereof. There be ſome thinges alſo, in the holy ſcriptures, ſo profoundly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that euery one maye not lawfullye procéede ſo farre. To be ſhort, there be ſome things alſo written in ſuch terms, that (as <hi>Augustin</hi> ſaith) it ſhold appeare the holy ghoſt would whet our diligence in the ſerching and meditating of them. And vnleſſe the neceſſarie points of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and Chriſtian religion were ſo playnely and clearly: to be ſhort, ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly
<pb facs="tcp:1688:29"/> declared in the writings of the Prophetes and Apoſtles, that they may be (the holy ghoſt being preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t amongſt them, whereby God lightneth all his ſayntes) manifeſtly vnderſtoode in the Church, to what end, ſhoulde the Lorde haue ſent his hearers to the ſcriptures? Yea that more is, to what ende haue, both the Prophets and Chriſte himſelfe alſo, and the Apoſtles ſpoken, if they would not haue theſe thinges, to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, which all ought to know?</p>
            <p>I will ſpeake ſomething more bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which yet I hope I can proue.<note place="margin">VVe cannot by naturall vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding knovv, vvhat the pointes of Chriſtian religion are, but by the writinges of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles.</note> That we may conſent vnto the points of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian religion, as vnto true groundes, and muche more that wee may applye them vnto our ſelues, it behooueth ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that wee ſhoulde haue our eares elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where opened, <hi>a fleſhly beart giuen vs, to be ſhort, that we ſhould elſewhere be taught tban of fleſh and blood,</hi> becauſe the church, is the congregation of them, <hi>that must be taught of God, &amp; to whome the arme of the Lord is reuealed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſai. 53.1.</note> and that men may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, what the Prophetes and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, haue briefly thought and taught,
<pb facs="tcp:1688:30"/> concerning euery article of our religion, they haue neede, not onely of a wit in ſome meaſure ſharpened, but alſo of the knowledge of tongues, and of careful and diligent reading.</p>
            <p>For it is one manner of thing, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande, what this or that man ſayth, then ſo to vnderſtand the things, which thou doeſt perceiue, that thou alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue of them:<note place="margin">Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, knowledge, and full per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, muſt be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed in the holy ſcriptures of which that, to wit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, is naturall, the other is in deede ſpiritual, but alſo commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates: The third is proper to the children of God.</note> and not onely that thou vnderſtand what the thing is, but alſo wherefore it is: and comprehenſion is another thing, than knowledge, euen in prophane matters: and agayne in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of diuinity this knowledge is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, than full perſwaſion, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore comprehenſion belongeth vnto all men that are endued with ſome iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and vnto knowledge, there is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired alſo an outwarde lightning of Gods ſpirite, by reaſon of the blindenes of mans iudgment, which gift notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is common as well to many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, as to many good men. But ful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, doth ſeperate the choſen chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God from the caſtawayes, and is the proper riches of the Saintes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1688:30"/>
            <p>Therefore we require,<note place="margin">In what points we doe at this day diſſent, when the queſtion is demaunded, touching the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of Gods word.</note> the expoſition of the worde of God, not onely as profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, but alſo as neceſſary, yet not for the ſame cauſe, as theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thinke, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet wil wee fet it from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whome theſe men ſuppoſe we wil take it, for they think that that worde is ſo darkly deliuered, that (as thogh it were ſome darke thing) it ſhould neede light, fetcht elſewhere then from it ſelfe, and when we demand of them, from whence at the length this light ſhould be fet, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they lay vnto vs, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vizard or bare ſhewe of the Catholique Church, vnder which name ſomtimes, they lay before the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, theſe or thoſe of the Fathers: ſometimes the fragments of particular or general counſels: to bee ſhort, they lay before them very often, long cuſtom for an argument that cannot bee refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to which thinges, if a man doe not forthwith conſent, he is now layde open to the ſlaughter of the outragious people (no knowledge of his cauſe beeing had before) as thogh he were guilty of ſome haynous crime, committed againſt God or man, wheras in times paſt, he was
<pb facs="tcp:1688:31"/> condemned to bee burned, vnder ſome certaine colour of law.</p>
            <p>And in deede this is now their zeale. But we, (that we may in one word de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare all thinges which belong to this matter) ſay, that the Church of Chriſte, is a ſchoole, in which the worde of the Lorde is not onely barely to be read, as out of the letter written, but alſo to bee taught, that it maye bee rightly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode, and ſo to be taught, that exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, corrections and conſolations, both openly and priuately, maye bee vſed, which in <hi>Paul</hi> is vnderſtoode by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of <hi>Prophecying.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.6.</note> Moreouer this alſo wee adde, which thing ought here chiefly to bee marked, that the interpretation of thoſe ſcriptures, are to be ſet, no where elſe, then out of the ſcriptures themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, not onely becauſe the word of God, is able to giue credite to it ſelfe: but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, becauſe that trueth is reuealed vnto vs no where els, then in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> writings of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophetes and Apoſtles, For that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Austen</hi> is well knowen, and is moſt true, <hi>That the ſcripture is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by the ſcripture:</hi> Neither ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:1688:31"/> it irke me heere to put downe, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notable place, out of the 49. <hi>Homelie,</hi> of the imperfect worke vpon <hi>Mathew,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it agreeth altogeather with our times. <hi>He that will know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which is the true Church of Christ, let him not know it but onely by the ſcriptures.</hi> And by and by after. <hi>Christians therefore, beeing willing to receiue, the certainetie of true fayth, let them flie to nothing but to the ſcriptures, otherwiſe if they ſhall haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to other thinges, they ſhall stumble &amp; perish, not vnderstanding, which is the true Church: and by this meanes they shall fall into the abhomintaion of deſolation, which ſtandeth in the holy places of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to whom ſhall belong (will theſe men ſay) the interpretation of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? Verily all be not Prophetes, all be not teachers. But againe.<note place="margin">Eſay.</note> 
               <hi>Eſay as cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that both Priestes and Prophetes, haue erred in their viſion:</hi> neither would Chriſt haue admoniſhed,<note place="margin">Math. 16.6. Math. 23.2.</note> 
               <hi>That the leauen of the Phariſes, should be auoyded,</hi> if we ſhoulde without exception, haue conſented vnto them, <hi>That ſit in Moſes chayre:</hi> Neither ſhould the falſe Prophetes be eſchued, if
<pb facs="tcp:1688:32"/> all the Prophetes did ſpeake the truth: neither would <hi>Caiphas,</hi> and the whole Synode of the Prieſtes, haue condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Chriſt, if the holy Ghoſt, had beene tried without exception to thoſe, that ſit in <hi>Aarons</hi> ſeat: What then?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Antiquitye or noueltye maketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, to inſtruct men to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the true inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of ſcripture from the falſe.</note>Let theſe men therefore heare at length, that which we haue ſo often times cryed out vnto deafe men: to wit, that we do not ſimply reiect, neither the old nor the new counſels, whether they be particular or generall, vnleſſe they be plainly theeuiſh: that we do not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply refuſe, neither old nor new writers, vnles they be manifeſtly, either ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tious or ridiculous, or by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon conſent abrogated: That we doe not ſimply caſt from vs, the writings, neither of aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent nor new writers, whether they be Eccleſiaſticall or Laicall (as theſe men call them, for God is no accepter of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and often times euen by the baſeſt ſorte, he confoundeth the pride of the moſt wiſe), vnleſſe they be plainly wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſuperſtitious or fooliſhe. But this onely we require, which the moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and euery the moſt religious of the
<pb facs="tcp:1688:32"/> old writers, moniſh carefully to be don, to wit, that all theſe thinges, ſhould be diligently examined, according to the rule of the written word of God. For antiquitie and authoritie of thoſe that wryte, may in deed ſet ſome collour of truth vpon falſhood, but that it ſhoulde be true, which diſagreeth neuer ſo little from the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles, that truely it can neuer bring to paſſe. Furthermore,<note place="margin">The Creeds of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Synodes &amp; the iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of the fathers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, are at no hand re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected by vs: yea rather, they are ſtrongly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not as yeelding credite themſelues.</note> experience it ſelf more than ſufficiently declareth, that there haue beene long time ſince, <hi>builded vpon the foundation layd by the Apostles, not onely bay and stubble, but alſo yron and rust,</hi> to be ſhort, lies vppon trueth: All which thinges, muſte at the length be conſumed by the light and fire of Gods word.</p>
            <p>Now leaſt theſe men ſhoulde agayne complaine, that what ſoeuer hath bene eſtabliſhed by counſell after conſell, in the auncient Churche, ſhoulde by this meanes be called into doubt: we confes, that we doe acknowledge the Créedes, which were alwayes approoued by the common conſent of the whole Church,
<pb facs="tcp:1688:33"/> to wit, the Creed of the Apoſtles, <hi>Nice, Athanaſius</hi> his creed, the creed of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople, Chalcedon,</hi> togeather with the curſes pronounced in the ſecond counſel of <hi>Epheſus</hi> againſte <hi>Nestorius:</hi> And that we both with mouth and hart deteſt, al hereſies, which either by open or ſecret conſent of the whole Church, were out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God, condemned in thoſe 4. councels, and alſo ouer throwen, in the fifth and ſixth councels of <hi>Constantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> And all other hereſies whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, which afterwarde, eyther newlye ſprong vp, or are newly poliſhed, not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the truth hangeth vpon any Synods or Creedes, but becauſe we acknowledge, that the thinges which are preſcribed and eſtabliſhed in them,<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the true Chriſt, who is the only, true, perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſary note of the true Church.</note> may be rightly iudged, by the writings of the prophets and Apoſtles: ſo far of is it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the authority of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, or diſpiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſent of the godly, either ancient or new writers, which thing our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, falſly &amp; ſhamleſly obiect vnto vs.</p>
            <p>Now the ſumme of al theſe things is this, that Chriſt is the true, perpetual, neceſſary: &amp; to be ſhort, the onely marke
<pb facs="tcp:1688:33"/> of the Church: yea I ſay, the true Chriſt that is, ſuche a one, as he from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning hath moſt perfectly (touching the matter and maner of ſaluation, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed him ſelfe, both in the writings, of the prophets and of the Apoſtles.<note place="margin">Mat. 12.13.</note> For that ſaying ſtandeth ſure: <hi>He that ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth not with me, ſcattereth abroad:</hi> and that ſaying,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>that christ is that corner stone of the foundation, vppon whome the whole building riſeth vp:</hi> And that onely head, which miniſtreth vnto his body, that is vnto the true catholique Church, al fée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and mouing: To be ſhort,<note place="margin">Iohn. 10.7. Iohn. 14.6. Iohn. 11.25.</note> 
               <hi>he is the dore, the way, the reſurrection, and the lyfe.</hi> Therfore, wherſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> word is heard, as it ought to be, there in deed Chriſte raigneth, and where Chriſte raigneth, there in deed we iudge the Catholique, viſible Churche to be, neither tied to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny certaine place, nor vnto the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: for <hi>where that dead carkas is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24.28.</note> to wit Chriſte crucified, there be thoſe Egles: there is ſaluation,<note place="margin">Act. 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>where that onely name is, in which we must be ſaued:</hi> there be the children of light, <hi>where that ſonne ſhineth there be the true sheepe. Where the voyce of
<pb facs="tcp:1688:34"/> that ſheepeheard is heard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.20.</note> 
               <hi>although two or three onely, throughout all the world, shall be truely gathered together in his name:</hi> And to ſpeake in fewe wordes, where that true ſeede is ſowen, there is the Lords field: and there that harueſt gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, which ſhall neuer be burned.</p>
            <p>But againe, becauſe it falleth out, partly thorough the weakneſſe of mans wit, euen in the moſte excellent men, partly through the wickeneſſe or negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the paſtors, that ſcarce at any time, ſince y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of the Apoſtles, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Chriſt, hath beene ſo preached in the Church, but that ſome blemiſh, hath priuely crept in, (which thing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to bee done, euen by the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of the Apoſtles, and that whileſt they alſo were liuing: Finally, becauſe the Lord hath apointed, not onely that the worde ſhoulde be taught: but alſo that it ſhoulde not be taught of euery man: And for this cauſe, hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted certaine lawes, touching this order. I muſt here again declare two things: to wit, how farre it ſhoulde be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that that onely marke of the true
<pb facs="tcp:1688:34"/> Church, that is to ſay, the preaching of Gods worde, ſhoulde be pure, and how much we ſhould giue, to the ordination and ſucceſſion of the Paſtors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p>Therefore,<note place="margin">How farre it is neceſſary that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of fayth, ſhould be pure in the Church. that the Church ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar or gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, may be a true church.</note> as touching that former point, I put downe three thinges. One is, that although there be nothing ſet out vnto vs in the holy Scriptures, which is not moſt profitable and verie neceſſary as it were vnto ſaluation: yet there are certaine chiefe points, and as it were grounds of our religion, which are to be diſcerned from the reſt. The ſecond point is, that there haue beene ſome matters, which in times paſt haue beene rudimentes of the Catholique Churche, and may in other times alſo be rudiments of ſome particular chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, yet for all that thoſe points ceaſe not, to belong to the true Churche. The third is, that the religion and marke of the Churche, either vniuerſall or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, is not to be meaſured by ſome thing, that this or that Paſtor teacheth by worde or writing: neither by that, that ſome ſheepe by them ſelues haue
<pb facs="tcp:1688:35"/> thought this: Or by the diſputations of ſome, whether they be many or few, but by that doctrine, which is commonly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in the Churches, ſo that it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable to the word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">That all the points of chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, are not of the foundation thereof.</note>Now becauſe theſe queſtions are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into controuerſie, go to, let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme them by ſure reaſons &amp; examples. As touching the firſte, the thing it ſelfe ſheweth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there may be variaunce tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ſome things, &amp; yet the ſoundation of chriſtian religion, remaine ſafe: And againe ſome things cannot be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, but that the whole building, be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ouerthrown. <hi>He that denieth Christ to haue come in the fleshe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>is not of God, but is the ſpirit of Antichrist.</hi> Therefore the companies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">They deni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed Chriſt, to haue come in the flesh.</note> 
               <hi>Dochitae,</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioniſtes of whome he ſpeaketh here, did hold that Chriſt was not true man.</note> 
               <hi>Marci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onits,</hi> and of ſuch like, be not the Church of Chriſte, whereby it is prooued, that the point, touching both the natures of Chriſte, is an article of Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, belonging to the foundation. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the Churche of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in who was better learned, than <hi>Peter</hi>) knew not the calling of the vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, and yet what true Churche was
<pb facs="tcp:1688:35"/> there then in the worlde, if the Church of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> were not it? Therefore the point concerning the calling of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed, is not of it ſelfe, of the points of Chriſtian religion, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the foundation. Therfore, there is ſome difference betweene thoſe thinges which are ſet forth vnto vs in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to be beléeued.</p>
            <p>The ſecond alſo may be prooued, by a more euident example. For who doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth,<note place="margin">That there are ſome ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments of particular Churches. VVhich thing alſo in times paſt fall out, in the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique church.</note> but that if euer there were any where, a true, and almoſt onely and wholy Catholique Churche, that was Chriſtes owne houſhold, being conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt and that according to the fleſhe, with thoſe his twelue diſciples? Who likewiſe is ignoraunt, that the point of the reſurrection (the foundation wherof is the reſurrection of Chriſt himſelfe) is of ſo great waight, that the Apoſtle doth rightly pronounce, that (that beeing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed) the whole fruit of the Goſpell, ſhoulde be aboliſhed? but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> very congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation could ſcarce beleue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt was yet riſen. And <hi>Thomas</hi> gaue not credite, to his own very fellow diſciples: yea the
<pb facs="tcp:1688:36"/> diſciples, would not haue beléeued, euen their owne verye eyes, if the Lorde had not ſayd,<note place="margin">Luke. 24.39. VVe may not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of the falshood or truth of any church by the doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther many or few.</note> 
               <hi>A ſpirit hath not fleſh and bones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that third thing is confirmed, by the examples of the Churches of <hi>Achaia</hi> and <hi>Galatia,</hi> which doubtleſſe, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle would not haue called the churches of Chriſt, and therefore true churches, if hee had therfore thought that the church of <hi>Corinth</hi> had denied that article of the reſurrection of the fleſh: &amp; the churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> had reiected the benefite of their liberty, purchaſed by Chriſte, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome in <hi>Corinth,</hi> yea perhaps ſome of the paſtors themſelues, did doubt of the poynte of the reſurrection: and the moſt part of the <hi>Galathians,</hi> called backe agayn the vſe of circumciſion and other ceremonies, ſeeing that yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.2.</note> the ſame <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth: <hi>If ye be circumciſed, Christ doth profite you nothing:</hi> and ſeeing that he affirmeth that thoſe which vrged circumciſion, not of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but of ſtubbornnes, <hi>they were remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued alway vnto another goſpel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 1.6. Phil. 3.2.</note> &amp; therefore he openly calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Apoſtatates or fal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers away, and compareth them <hi>to Dogs,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1688:36"/> that is to ſay, to vncleane beaſtes. But it is an other thing, to erre through ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>aunce, than obſtinately to reſiſt the truth, as wiful fellowes are wont. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie which is without the Church, if it be of ſome point of the religion, that toucheth the foundation, is an other thing, than being deceiued or an error, which requireth and ſuffereth it ſelfe to be taught. To be ſhorte, the Eclipſe of the Sunne, is an other thing, than the abſence of the ſame: and the euening is an other thing than the darkeneſſe of the night: yea the night it ſelfe, which the day ſucceedeth, is an other thing than the darkneſſe were,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>when they coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the depth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things then being put downe,<note place="margin">That ſome errours may creepe into the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique church yea and that in ſome point of faith, which concerneth the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> it ſhalbe eaſie to iudge, that euery error doth not take away the name of the true church, and with al that to be moſt falſe, which the aduerſaries ſay, to wit, that the Catholique Church ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not erre, and yet that euery error doth not abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the name of the Catholike Church. For as touching this latter point, if ſome particular Church may erre, euen
<pb facs="tcp:1688:37"/> in ſome chiefe head or article of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an religion, and yet it ceaſſeth not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be a true Church: wherefore ſhal not a man ſay the ſame of al particular Churches, not conſidered one by one, but vniuerſally, for this is the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church? Truely it is not probable that there liued then any men (when Chriſt roſe againe) better or more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly inſtructed in true faith, then thoſe twelue Diſciples: And yet we ſee this whole congregation, for a time (as I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen now ſayd) ſo to haue doubted of the reſurrection of Chriſt, that for that cauſe (as <hi>Luke</hi> writeth) <hi>Christ remayned with them fortie dayes after the reſurrection,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 1.3.</note> that he might fully aſſure them of his reſurrection. Wherefore this thing we conclude, that the chiefe points of our religion, ought of neceſſitie to remaine ſound, in the Catholique Church, that it maye be called Catholique: But there may ſome times fall in ſome cloud (ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially through the negligence of the Paſtors) which may ſome times dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, one while this, an other while that article, which neuer the leſſe (when the
<pb facs="tcp:1688:37"/> holy Ghoſt appeareth) ſtraight wayes vaniſheth away.</p>
            <p>Therefore Catholique is not, (as the vnlearned imagine) alwaies and with out exception the ſame, that right or ſound is, ſeeing that euen ſome vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall error, may continue for a time. And the ſame thing may and ought muche more to be ſpoken of the particular congregations of this vniuerſallitie. And if theſe things be true, euen in the very grounds of our religion: how much more, may wee thinke the ſame to bee true, as often as errours creepe in, by which the very foundations of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are not ouerthrown? And this is the ſtuble or chaffe which ſometimes (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>are builded vpon the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Apostles,</hi> which at the length ſhall vaniſh away, when the day of the Lord appeareth.</p>
            <p>But this day ſheweth it ſelfe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſooner, ſomtimes later. (So I had almoſt ſayde, all the Byſhops of <hi>Africa</hi> thought with <hi>Cyprian,</hi> that baptiſme ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred by heretikes, was of no force. Which thing, although it were falſe,
<pb facs="tcp:1688:38"/> might neuertheles (ſo long as the ſum of fayth remayneth ſound and vnhurt) be wrongfully taught and beléeued. But this errour continued not long. There is a like conſideration to be had of many traditions, which for that cauſe, began at the length, falſely to be called, and to be deemed Apoſtolicall, becauſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once confirmed by continuall vſe, they were ſuppoſed to haue come euen from the Apoſtles them ſelues: which traditions alſo, by reaſon therof, the day of the Lorde (which hath againe in our times ſhined forth) cannot now aboliſh, with out very great contentions. Be it therefore farre from any to thinke, that for ſuch maner of blemiſhes, ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations ſhould be thought, not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, to the bodye of the Catholique Churche,<note place="margin">That ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes at the firſt ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>times tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, ceaſe to be ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes, and grow to bee cankers.</note> although godly and diligent Paſtors, ſhoulde giue very great dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, that theſe ſpottes alſo ſhoulde be wiped away, with the ſponge of Gods word.</p>
            <p>But this thing firſt of al muſt here be marked, that theſe blemiſhes and as it were byles or ſwellings, do ſome times
<pb facs="tcp:1688:38"/> ſo farre increaſe, that they growe to a canker, and that they pull away the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry members from the body: which thing the moſt ſhamefull examples, both of auncient times, and alſo of our times, declare to haue fallen out, eſpecially by the fault of the paſtors. As for example, exorciſme or cuniuring (one ſort of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proper to them that were poſſeſſed with ill ſpirites, and an other common to all that were growen in yeares, and came from <hi>Paganiſme</hi> to Chriſtianitie, brought in alſo by the negligence of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, into the baptiſme of Infants, that were borne of Chriſtians) was at the beginning onely a blemiſh, and yet not being looked into of the old Byſhoppes, at the length increaſed ſo farre, that in the papacie it was retained as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and ſo became a wilworſhip, a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter now at no hand indifferent: And in ſome Churches, (although lightened with the Goſpell) it is retayned as not vnprofitable, with great ſhame (truely) to the paſtors: of ſo great importance is it in ſeaſon to preuent, euen the ſmaleſt errors.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1688:39"/>
            <p>The ceremonie of anoynting with oyle in baptiſme (which was miniſtred to thoſe that were as it were, to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Deuil, and the fleſhe) was in the beginning chaffe, but this chaffe, how farre in proceſſe of time it grewe, we ſee,<note place="margin">Chriſme in baptiſme prefered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore water, the element of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> when the Criſme alſo began to be reuerenced, which thing notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding did not fal out in the very wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a true and an eſſential ſigne of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. So it is manifeſt, that the ſigne of the croſſe, was at the beginning an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen profeſſion of chriſtianitie, the abuſe wherof at the laſt, brought to paſſe, that the very croſſe, was ſet vp, in the place of Chriſt crucified, neither is there any idolatry in all the worlde more deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. So the remembrances of martyrs, and the funerals of the more famous Byſhops, were celebrated, both with Orations in the praiſe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and with incredible concourſe of people, from whence by and by after ſprang vp inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of the dead, at their ſepulchers, and in proceſſe of time, the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinges of reliques alſo. The paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of walles, brought into the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb facs="tcp:1688:39"/> temples, about foure hundred yeares after the deathe of Chriſte, and that without any worſhip thereof, was in deed accounted, haie. But howe farre this blemiſh hath growne we ſee, inſomuch, that the ſecond of the ten com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandements, was vnder that colour, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly by the Papiſts blotted out: and (which thing cannot beſpoken, without the incredible ſhame of ſome) that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond commandement, is alſo at this day numbred, by certein men (which ſhould not ſo deale) amongeſt the ceremoniall commandementes. Such was in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, the lenten faſt, and ſome choiſe or difference of meates, without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of worſhip, added therto. Which things, we nowe ſee ſo eſtabliſhed, that ſundrye and thoſe no ſmall perſons, but ſuch as wil ſeeme to be moſt Catholike, do moſt obſtinately defende, that in the doing of them, conſiſteth in ſome reſpect, the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, yea the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of merites or power to deſerue. What I beſéech you, coulde ſeeme at the firſt, to haue been more indifferent then for the celebration of the ſupper, to haue
<pb facs="tcp:1688:40"/> a table of ſtone or of wood? But, if the <hi>Grecians</hi> in the celebration of the ſaide ſupper, had neuer vſed their<note n="*" place="margin">That is, their Altars dedicated to Deuils.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and the <hi>Latines</hi> their Alters, but had beene content with their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon tables (which was in vſe in the Apoſtles times) likely it is, that the controuerſie, touching that deteſtable idolatry of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe (by which we ſee, the whole worlde at this day, to be ſet on fire) could neuer haue ſprung vp.</p>
            <p>Now, to what end, tend theſe things? to wit, that firſt in deſcrying the marks of the true church, hereſies might be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed from errors, and haye &amp; ſtub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, from thoſe things, which eyther of themſelues, or by reaſon of the opinion of worſhip brought in, are either vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or ſuperſtitious: and yet that all the gouernours of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chucch, ought to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that as the alter, was not in time paſt to be builded of ſtones, garniſhed by the diligence of man: neither yet that it was lawfull for them, ſo much as to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten a naile in the Tabernacle, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the paterne which <hi>Moſes</hi> had ſeene in the mount: euen ſo now alſo, all
<pb facs="tcp:1688:40"/> godly magiſtrates indeede, and all true ſhepheards, ought to endeuour, that in reſtoring the temple of the Lord, by ſo many means fallen down, they ſhoulde not onely reſtore thoſe thinges, which haue beene ouerthrown by <hi>Antichrists,</hi> but alſo that they ſhould moſt diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye wipe awaye all, euen the lighteſt ſpottes, that haue proceeded from the ſame <hi>Antichrists,</hi> although they be, as it were waxen hard vpon the walles of the temple: and that marking (partly by the ſtory of former ages, and partly by the beholding of the preſent ruins of the Churche) theſe former euils of Satan, they ſhould at no hand ſuffer themſelues to be mocked, by the allegation of the fragmentes, of certaine of the auncient fathers, or by any vayn ſhew of cuſtom: but rather that they ſhould not leaue of, vntill by doctrine, both the Ceremonies and all the Eccleſiaſticall gouernment alſo, be apted, not vnto ſome figuratiue Image of ſhew, which was needful vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſchoolemaſterſhip of the law, but exactly framed, according vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſte perfect paterne, which the ſonne of God
<pb facs="tcp:1688:41"/> him ſelfe by his owne mouth &amp; his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles after him, haue moſte perfectly ſet forth vnto vs in their writings. But co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerning this matter, we wil elswhere ſpeake more fully (as I hope) when we ſhal anſwere thoſe notable meane men, who reprehend vs, as ouer ſeuere exac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> work, &amp; eſpecially whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhal ſeuerally anſwere, vnto the writing of <hi>Caſſander,</hi> to the end, al men may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that none more hinder the worke of the Lorde, than theſe <hi>Samaritans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">VVhich be the principal points of the Catholique faith or reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note>Now, becauſe I ſée ſome (not yéelding vnto theſe things, which we haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in general, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fundamental or principall points of our religion) again to dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what thoſe ſhold be: I anſwer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe articles are to be called grounds or principles, which being laid, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole building remaineth: &amp; which being ouer thrown, al things builded therupon fall to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground. And al theſe things, we pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fes to haue bene deſcribed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great ſhort<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; plainnes, out of the word of God in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Créed, which they cal the Apoſtles. Which thing ought to be added to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ten commandements, &amp; the Lords praier of
<pb facs="tcp:1688:41"/> the which, that, to wit, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ten commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, doth verie compendiouſly ſet out the order of Chriſtian life: and this, that is, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords praier, doth very briefly alſo ſet out, right inuocation and praier. This (I ſay) is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fundamental, true, and perpetuall mark of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Catholike church, which ſhall neuer bee blotted out vnto the worlds end: but which neuertheleſſe ought to be expounded, out of the wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Prophets and Apoſtles, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence it is taken, that al men may vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand it and keepe it, as much as in them lyeth.</p>
            <p>Now the order of this expoſition is 2.<note place="margin">VVhat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Catholique doctrine is required in the Church.</note> fold: one more familiar, which is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for al men: an other more large, and far more plentiful: as we ſée that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles creed, was afterwardes expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by ſome other Creedes of the holy Synodes, that hereſies might bee met withall, &amp; the Conſciences eſtabliſhed more and more in ſound doctrine. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, albeit that to the ende, that ſome man might be a true member of Chriſt, it be not neceſſary, that he ſhould moſt exactely vnderſtande, for what cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:1688:42"/> thinges are ſpoken and ſet downe, and ſhould know the determinations of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations in diuinitie: Yet euery one ought to know according to his capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, what he doth beleeue, and why he doth beleeue, and not to reſt in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiliſhe inuention of faith, which they call vnfolded, that is to beleeue, as the Churche hath determined, and to aſke no further: but to adde alſo vnto that familiar inſtruction, the expoſition of holy writings,<note place="margin">That the true, yea the Catholique church hath more then once wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and lawful mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and therefore that that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie and lawfull ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and ſucceſſion of Paſtors, vvas for a time broken off.</note> of which <hi>Paul</hi> ſetteth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs foure pointes 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. to wit, <hi>doctrine, reproofe, correction, and comfort.</hi> All which are by diligent Paſtors and teachers, publikely and priuately, to be applied, to the capacities of the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers.</p>
            <p>It remayneth that we declare, howe much we ought to giue to perſonal ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion and ordination. We haue ſayde, that the onely, true, perpetuall, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary marke of the catholique Church is that doctrine, which diuerſly, and ſundry maner of wayes, firſt by worde, and afterward by wrytings, hath bene deliuered by the Prophetes, and at the
<pb facs="tcp:1688:42"/> laſt moſt perfectly declared by Chriſte him ſelfe, and that by his owne mouth, and by his Apoſtles. For this word, as (euen after Chriſte him ſelfe), <hi>Peter</hi> ſayth, <hi>is that ſeede,</hi> by which the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Churche, both at the beginning of the world appeared, and by which alſo it ſhall continue, euen vnto the ende of the world. But ſeed is to no purpoſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be ſowen, and the Lorde, (who both vnder the olde, and vnder the new Teſtament, appoynted an order for the ſowing of this ſeed, by the miniſtry of men) hath (I ſay) neceſſarily appointed this ſowing (for otherwiſe the ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding abroade of this Churche woulde quickly end) to endure to the ende of the world: Be it ſo truely. Then thou wilt ſaye, ordination alſo and ſucceſſion of thoſe perſons, is a true, perpetuall, and neceſſary mark of the catholike church, agréeing altogether with that other, to wit, the mark of ſowing. So our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries do conclude, but falſly and fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For, (that I may let paſſe thoſe two thinges already confuted by vs, that is to ſay, becauſe they babble of the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:1688:43"/> of perſons, omitting the ſucceſſion of that Apoſtolicall doctrine: Moreouer becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d an other ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, than that which hath beene begun by the Apoſtles them ſelues) either they do not ſee, or they diſſemble that they do ſee (albeit the ſowing alſo, and the ſowers, are required no leſſe than the ſeede, to the tilling of this fielde of the Church) that the ſame order hath not alwaies bene kept, either of ſowing the ſeed, or of ordeyning them, vnto whome this ſowing is committed. And this not<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>withſtanding, they ought to haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, both by the fore tellings of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, and alſo by the holy hiſtories, which things remaineth to be proued of vs. The Church therfore I confes, was neuer without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God. But let theſe men alſo ſhew vs, that there hath bene ſome one, certaine, &amp; perpetual or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der both of that ſowing, &amp; of the perſons admitted to that ſowing, and that the ſame hath bene tied alſo at all times, to the ſame lawes of ordination, before that firſt the lord had conſecrated to him ſelfe the firſt begotten. <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.2. and 19
<pb facs="tcp:1688:43"/> 22. and the 24.5. in whoſe ſteed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that <hi>Leuiticall</hi> prieſthood was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, almoſt with infinit ceremonies. <hi>Num.</hi> 8.18. Therfore then at the length began, that certaine &amp; ordinary order of ſucceſſion &amp; ordination, that is, of ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and of thoſe vnto whom the charge of that ſowing was committed. Which ſucceſſion, and which maner of orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, if before that time the Church lac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked it, it is prooued, that that ordinary ſucceſſion and calling, hath neither bin alwaies neceſſary nor continual, ſéeing that the viſible Churche ſtood ſo many ages, before both of them,</p>
            <p>Now let vs ſee, whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Leuiticall</hi> prieſthood, hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, euen vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt. In deed we read, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſpreding abraod of <hi>Aarons</hi> poſterity, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued vntill the ouerthrow of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. But euen as we ſay, thogh <hi>Dauids</hi> ſtocke were not aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, yet <hi>Dauids</hi> kingdome (euen as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other the prophets, <hi>Ezechiel</hi> had foretold) was broken of, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dayes of <hi>Sedichia,</hi> vnto <hi>Zorobabel,</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe tims in ſteed of kings they were Dukes, and
<pb facs="tcp:1688:44"/> at the lengthe (the <hi>Aſmoney,</hi> taking all power vnto themſelues) <hi>Dauids</hi> poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I ſay, in ſtéede of Dukes became Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators, vntill at laſt they being alſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away by <hi>Herod</hi> a forrainer borne, and <hi>Iudea</hi> being reduced to a Prouince, and ſo in fine <hi>as Iacob had foretold (all go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment being taken from Iudea)</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſonne of <hi>Dauid</hi> ſprang vp,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.10.</note> to ſit in the throne of <hi>Dauid</hi> for euer: So it appeareth, that all the Leuiticall prieſthoode, was not at once broken off, vntil (the eternal prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of <hi>Melchizedech</hi> ſucceeding) it was wholy aboliſhed. For, (to let paſſe thoſe publique miſeries and ſlaughters of the people, vnder the iudges, and eſpecially that time which is ſpoken of, in the fiue laſt chapters of the ſtory of the Iudges, in which time it is euident that the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like miniſtery was greatly decaied, and ſometimes almoſte aboliſhed) who will deny, that there was any true church, in the kingdome of the ten tribes, from the time of <hi>Ieroboam</hi> the firſt king, vnto the ouerthrow of <hi>Samaria?</hi> and yet that there was no ſucceſſion, nor ordination of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitical prieſthood amongſt them, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="tcp:1688:44"/> by this, becauſe it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Leui,</hi> that he departed from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of the ten tribes: and by that ſame moſt heauy complaynt of <hi>Helias,</hi> which is reported by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.2. for concerning that which is reported afterwardes of theſe hundred prophetes, hid in a caue. 1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 18.13. it doth not prooue, that there was there, any ordinarye mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery.</p>
            <p>The aduerſaries will reply, that the godly <hi>Iſraelites</hi> went to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and therefore, that they perteined to the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiticall prieſthoode. Bee it ſo that ſome went, yet there was ſome true Churche then, in the kingdome of the ten tribes, not going to the Citie, neyther vſing the ordinarye ſacrifices, nor reteining anye vſe of the Leuiticall prieſthoode.</p>
            <p>But agayne theſe men ſay, they had notwithſtanding colledges of prophets, and aſſemblies of Godly men alſo, at their appointed dayes, as appeareth namely out of the 2. <hi>Kings.</hi> 4.23. and therefore the ordinary ſucceſſion of the miniſtery, did not then ceaſe, And ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe I conclude out of this place,
<pb facs="tcp:1688:45"/> that there was then no holy miniſtry in the kingdome of <hi>Iſraell.</hi> But this one thing I gather, that the ſucceſſion of the <hi>Leuiticall</hi> miniſtry (which was the onely ordinarye miniſterye) was then all togeather broken off, in the kingdome of <hi>Iſraell.</hi> For neither were the Prophetes ordained by the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrye of men, neither was their order continuall.</p>
            <p>They will againe reply, that an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſucceſſion may ceaſe, in particular Churches: but at no hand in the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique church, that is to ſay, vniuerſally: ſeeing that then alſo the temple conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in the kingdome of <hi>Iudah.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that, I can replie out of the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie of the Prophetes, that <hi>Iudah</hi> ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haued hir ſelfe, not onely in maners, but alſo in the very worſhippe of God, that <hi>she iustified Iſraell hir ſelfe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 16.51.</note> and that alſo the temple of the Lorde was ſhut vp vnder <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> after that it had beene imbrued, with the blood of the Prophetes: and that horrible idolatry declared vnto <hi>Ezechiel</hi> in a viſion: beſide theſe things I ſay, I furthermore adde
<pb facs="tcp:1688:45"/> two other: one is, that if ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church may be a member of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church (without the marke of ſucceſſion, and ordinary ordination) it neceſſarily followeth that thoſe notes, are not that, which the <hi>Logitians</hi> cal pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, after the fourth ſort: that is to ſay, a terme that alwayes agreeth vnto one kinde, and to euery particular of the ſame kind, whereof we now demaund, and in deed doe iuſtly demand it, ſéeing the whole force of the definition, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth properly, in the knowledge of the difference. The other is, that if (which thing we haue ſhewed before) ſome parte of the Catholique Churche, may lacke that ſucceſſien, and ordinary ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for a tyme, it followeth that that thing maye fall out in all parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and ſeuerall Churches. For why ſhoulde it fall out to one, rather than to an other? But where this thinge ſhall fall out, in what generall thing I praye you, maye a man finde that, which he wanteth not in all and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſingular parte of the ſame?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1688:46"/>
            <p>But leaſt theſe men ſhould agayn cry out, that yet that thing hath not fallen, which might haue fallen out. Let vs proceede further, and let vs conſider, what the ſtate of the Cotholike Church was, vnder the captiuitie of <hi>Babilon.</hi> Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely theſe men ſhall neuer prooue, that there was then any ordinary miniſtery of the Leuites. For the fable of <hi>Suſanna</hi> is confuted, out of the true ſtory of <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> ſo that it muſt be a narration either fabulous, or meerely allegoricall: euen as alſo the booke of <hi>Iudith</hi> is. And though <hi>Ezechiel</hi> ſometimes in ſome place, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed the office of a Prophete (as it is manifeſt by his Prophecies) yet by that it ſhall at no hande bee proued, that the Leuiticall Prieſthoode was not diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued.</p>
            <p>But thou wilt ſay, Circumciſion then continued. I graunt it, for this was the ſinguler benefite of God: euen as Satan could not (in our time, and in the time of our Fathers) bring to paſſe, but that the Sacrament of Baptiſme ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne. But the ſelfe ſame Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was not vſed thoſe forty yeeres, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:1688:46"/> the time of their wandering in the wildernes, where notwithſtanding if the Catholike Church were not, it was no where. Seing therefore the Churche may for a time want ſome ſacraments, truely this part of the publique mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterye, is not abſolutely, the perpetuall and neceſſary marke of the Churche: which thing yet cannot be ſayde, of the ſeede of the word it ſelfe, for the patent it ſelfe of a couenaunt, is another thing, than the ſeale put to the patent it ſelfe: ſo that the church, may for a time lacke this, by reaſon of many letts caſt in the way: but that, to wit, the worde, it can neuer lacke, although he that diſpiſeth that, to wit the Sacrament, deſpiſeth both, and therefore ſhall worthily bee iudged out of the Couenant.</p>
            <p>What then? truely the Church, can neither at any time lack the ſéeds of the word, neither the ſowing, nor the ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: but yet the ſluggiſhneſſe and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes of the Paſtors chiefly hindereth, that we cannot reſtraine both the ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and the ſowers to an ordinarie ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion and calling. And this thing fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb facs="tcp:1688:47"/> out, by two meanes. By one, when the chayres or places be not empty, but they which ſit in them, haue entred in, either by the doore, or by the window, and do either wholly neglect their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or mingle cockell with ſeed, or els ſowe nothing but poyſon: as ſuch was the ſtate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ancient catholique church, vnder the moſte parte of the vacant go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernments of the iudges: afterwards in <hi>Iuda</hi> vnder the moſte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings, and at the length, in the times of Chriſt being conuerſant vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth. By the other, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as that ordinary both ſowing, and alſo ordinary calling of ſowers ceaſeth, being for a time as it were, more than halfe dead (for we doe not acknowledge that theſe things, can all together be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed before the ende of the worlde) and ſuch was, as we haue ſayd, the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde forme and face of the Church of the tenne Tribes, and of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, in the captiuitie of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay therefore, that the very ſame thing, hath ſome times thorow the iuſt iudgement of God, fallen out in the
<pb facs="tcp:1688:47"/> Churche, in reſpect of the ſowing, and the ſowers, which often times falleth out in the times of famine and warre, to wit, that there is vtterly no place for ſowing. Which when it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe al do not yet die, but the hunger ſtaruen that remaine, are relieued, by the fruits gathered in the harueſt of the former yeares, euen as heretofore, in the times of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> the <hi>Egiptians</hi> did ſow nothing, but in the very ſeuenth yeare of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. So it behooued <hi>Daniell, Ezechiell, Zorobabell, Ezra, Nehemia,</hi> and the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt of the godly in <hi>Babylon,</hi> when an ordinary miniſtry was wanting, to be Prophetes and Paſtors vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, ioyning with moſt feruent prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers the continuall reading and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the holy ſcriptures, as in that ſtory, we reade to haue bene done, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we woulde rather ſay, that <hi>Moſes</hi> and the other Prophetes (whoſe wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges were then extant, although they them ſelues were dead long a goe) were notwithſtanding their Paſtors in this exile, vntill the Lord in his time, ſhould haue mercy vpon <hi>Syon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1688:48"/>
            <p>But amongeſt theſe breaches of the Church,<note place="margin">That the mark of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion and ordinarie vocation, is nor aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery fault that may fall out in the miniſter.</note> there is yet muche difference. For where the Paſtors doe their duties onely negligently, or elſe offend only in manners, neuertheles the double mark of the Church, which is ordinary and to be ſéen, remayneth. By the double mark of the Church I mean, the ſéed, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing, and alſo ordination, if ſo bee that theſe Paſtors, although negligent, bee notwithſtanding lawfully called. And if they mingle only ſome leauen, <hi>The lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is to be taken beede off,</hi> but the paſtors notwithſtanding are to be hard, ſo farre foorth, as they ſit vppon the chayre, not of <hi>Peter,</hi> but of Chriſt: neither doth ſuch a congregation, therefore ceaſſe, to bee deemed as a member of the Catholique Churche, (or els the Catholique viſible Church is no where) although perhaps no other, but negligent Paſtors, corrupt in maners, and mixing ſome leauen, be found throughout all the whole worlde. Such were in the times of Chriſte, the Phariſees and Saduces, and the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Lawe, whoſe Leauen hee teacheth,<note place="margin">Math. 16.6.</note> 
               <hi>must bee auoyded,</hi> which yet hee
<pb facs="tcp:1688:48"/> commaundeth to bee hearde,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>So long as they ſit in Moſes Chaire.</hi> But this place peraduenture, is not of euery one dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently inoughe marked: for it is to bee noted, oute of other places, that the writinges of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, were reade bee piecemeale in the Synagogues. Which thing, the Sections noted, euen at this daye, by a true order in the <hi>Hebrewe</hi> Bybles, doe declare. Nowe, vnto this pure and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere reading, was added an interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; full of Leauen: of which ſorte are theſe pointes which eſpeciallye in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> are plentifully confuted by Chriſt. Therefore Chriſt commaundeth thoſe thinges to bee heard out of the Pulpit, which were by cuſtome, ſyncerely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited out of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophetes, in the Synagogues: but the Leauen, wherewith they did corrupt, the puritye of Doctrine, to be eſchewed. So it is not to bee doubted, but that that outwarde Worſhippe in the Temple, was in the times of Chriſte, diligently exerciſed without Idolatry, which alſo Godly men did diligentlye perfourme, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:1688:49"/> the right vſe of the ſacrifices, and of the whole lawe, was vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by the iuſticiarie Phariſees, and by the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>duces, which denied the reſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rection, that is to ſay, the chiefe ende of ſacrifices. What maner of marchandize of high prieſtes office, there was then, and that againſte the preſcript of the lawe, appeareth by hiſtoryes. But this fault of perſons, in ſo great confuſion of thinges, did not aboliſhe the very facts of the prieſthoode, which did depend, not vpon the prieſt, but vpon the ordinance of God. For there is ſome certain mean thing betweene men meerely pryuate, and men lawfully called: to wit, when as ſome (exerciſing the place of thoſe that be lawfully called) are either tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ignoraunce, or thorow winking at them, borne with al: and in their name execute ſome publique office, as we read, that it was ordayned in the lawe of the <hi>Romans,</hi> concerning one <hi>Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Philippus,</hi> of which matter we haue in an other place ſpoken more fullye. Therefore the Church in deed retayned (and that in Phariſiiſme and Sadu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme)
<pb facs="tcp:1688:49"/> hir note, both of Gods ſeed, and in ſome ſort alſo, of the very ſowing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, although it were ſome what defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and yet neyther Phariſijſme nor Saducijſme, was a parte of the ſound Church.</p>
            <p>But as often as euen openly,<note place="margin">In the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh church ſuch a one as now a good while it hath been, all the notes of the true Catholique Church, are not in ſome ſort defaced onely, but euen vtterly taken away, as was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolde by the Apoſtles.</note> the chayre of truth is vtterly deſtroyed, ſo that on the one ſide ſyncere breade is not propounded vnto vs, ſo that a man maye receiue it: and on the other ſide, ſome Leauen, is ſo ſet before vs, that a man may not reiect it, but poyſons are drunke to men vnwilling of the ſame, who will account the congregation of theſe Wolues (or of thoſe which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe them) for the true eyther Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique or particular Churche. Now I affirme, that the Popedome, that is to ſaie, the Churche of <hi>Rome</hi> (as at this daie they call it) hath by little and little growen to be ſuche a one. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that thoſe thinges beeing in deed fulfylled, which both <hi>Paule</hi> 1. <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> 2. And alſo <hi>Iohn</hi> in the diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Image of the beaſte, haue now ſo many yeares paſte, ſet before
<pb facs="tcp:1688:50"/> our eyes to behold: and the auncient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, both <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>Irene, Chriſostome, Hierome, Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine, Becla,</hi> and <hi>Cardinall Cuſan</hi> himſelfe alſo, haue interpreted the ſame of the ſeat of <hi>Rome.</hi> For which of thoſe three markes of the catholique Church (wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of we haue ſhewed, that one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is vnmoueable and perpetuall, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we haue declared alſo to be ſome time diſcontinued) remaineth in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Church? For to ſpeake firſt of that proper, perpetuall, and abſolutly neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary marke, that is, the holy word wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſeeing that that is in the popiſhe Church, is not ſet forth vnto the people, but torne in ſundry péeces, and that alſo in a ſtrange tongue: and further, ſeeing that their ſhameleſneſſe hath proceeded ſo far, that they can not beare the ſame to be turned, into vulgare &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, neither yet indure, that the <hi>Latin</hi> interpretation being barbarous, and in many places falſe, ſhoulde be amended, by the <hi>Hebrue</hi> and, <hi>Greek</hi> copies, is there any man, vnleſſe he be by the iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God blinded, that will iudge
<pb facs="tcp:1688:50"/> theſe men, to be the Catholique Church (in which onely there is ſaluation) and not rather take it to be that <hi>Babylon,</hi> out of which all, that will not periſh ought to depart? But ſome amongſt them ſay. We do not onely receiue the writinges of the Prophetes and Apoſtles, but alſo receiue them, and in deed receiue them more large, than yee receiue them. For for one and two places ſake, they ad the bookes which are <hi>Apocripha.</hi> As though in deed to haue books decked with gold and precious ſtones, to worſhip papers tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſformed into idols, to ſing in a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge tongue, parcels torn in ſundry peces, or to hang them about the necke, or to vſe them in magical inchantments, be the ſame, that it is to teach the writings of the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles, and by theſe to direct, the whole ſeruice of God, and to be ſhort, by theſe to order, the whole life of man.</p>
            <p>But againe they ſaye we haue euery ſunday ſermons, and the readinges alſo and homelies of the Doctors: and to be ſhort, admonitions (as they call them) in pariſhes Yea, haue truly. But when
<pb facs="tcp:1688:51"/> what maner ones, of whome, and to what end are they had?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Note.</note>Now, to comprehend all thinges in a few words, ſeeing there be three wayes of corrupting the holy books of ſcripture, one is, when ſome thing is taken away from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the ſecond is, when ſome thing is added to them: the third, when ſome thing is changed in them. Who at the length ſeeth not, that theſe men are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as guilty of ſo many ſortes of falſehood?</p>
            <p>That I may beginne with the law. That vnwriten word, which they haue deuiſed &amp; wil haue to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chifeſt part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruice of God, &amp; that authority which they take to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, to make lawes to bynd mens conſciences, by what name ſhal we call it? Now, haue they not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly blotted out, without any ſhame, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond commandement, to the ende they might openly and manifeſtly, renew al kind of idolatrie, while they haue chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the names onely of ancient Idols? Haue they not oppreſſed the miſerable conſciences of Chriſtians, both by new and directly repugnant traditions? and
<pb facs="tcp:1688:51"/> vnder that cloake,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.14.</note> 
               <hi>Haue they not deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red widowes houſes onely (as in times past the Phariſees did):</hi> but alſo haue ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp empires and kingdomes? To be ſhorte, haue they not ouerthrowen from the very foundations, the vſe and end of the law?</p>
            <p>And in the Goſpell (the other and the chiefeſt part of Gods word) what haue they left ſound? Firſt, what maner of Chriſt do they ſet forth vnto vs? verely, a chriſt now in deed indued with a body without a body? do they propound him,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30.</note> 
               <hi>as he which was made of God vnto vs wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome?</hi> Yea for ſooth, ſo far as he helpeth our natural light. Do thei propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d him as our whole righteouſneſſe? for ſooth ſo farre as this thing is attributed to vs, who are therto prepared, partly of our ſelues, and partly by grace, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of eternall life, may, by deſert be aſcribed vnto the deſeruinges of oure righteouſneſſe. But what if our owne deſeruinges be not ſufficient? Verely, the deſeruings of ſome certaine ſaints (whoſe treaſure is not yet in deede drawen drie) purchaſed by a certayne
<pb facs="tcp:1688:52"/> price at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hand of theſe brokers, ſhal be added vnto vs. And the merites of what ſaints I beſech you, do they ſet forth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs? ſurely, ſuch as the Biſhoppes of <hi>Rome</hi> them ſelues, ſhal put into their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender, and ſuch as euery one ſhal chuſe to him ſelfe for Patrones and interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors. But doe they propound Chriſt as our ſanctification? yea for ſooth againe, ſo far as he augmenteth the remnants of our naturall holineſſe. Doe they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound him, as our onely redemption? in deed they doe it in worde, but performe nothing leſſe in deed. For they except y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſatiſfaction of puniſhment, which being granted, they make God himſelfe moſt vniuſt. For what is more wicked, than to require of him, which is not in fault, ſatiſfacory of puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts? And to what <hi>ende hath the Lorde borne our ſinnes vppon the tree?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſai. 53.4.5.</note> to what <hi>end hath our chastiſment rested vpon him?</hi> But now, ſeeing we are come to thoſe ſatiſfactions, doe they not moſt manifeſtly mocke with God and men, when they teach, that in the ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kling of coniured water, in tapers, in ſpittle, in oyle, in the ſigne of the croſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:1688:52"/> in choyce of meates, in the murmuring vp alſo of certaine prayers not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, in the praiers of counterfeit ſaints for the moſt part in the worſhipping of images, in the ringing of bels, in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine kinde of apparel alſo, and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death ſuche ſatiſfactions doe conſiſt? what more? O the moſte abhominable wickedneſſe that hath at any time bene committed of any man) in the very real offering of Chriſt him ſelf for the quick and the dead, which is therfore ſo much the more effectuall, as they ſay by how muche it is the more often reiterated, but in deed, is an open &amp; manifeſt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnder foot, of the ſacrifice, made once for vs: when they teach I ſay, that ſatiſfaction for the puniſhment of ſins, may be bought at theyr hands, both for vs that liue, and alſo for them that be dead, ſcorched in that their fier of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory? What maner of thing therefore is this Goſpell? And what manner of Chriſte is this of the Romiſhe Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? Who alſo perceiueth not, by the conference of the word of god, that theſe men, by their doctrine of <hi>Opus operatum,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1688:53"/> that is of the worke wrought, haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowen all the vſe of ſacraments? That I may ſaye nothing of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of the trueth of Chriſte his bodye, of his Aſcention into heauen, and of the article of his deſcending out of heauen. And that by the opinion of Tranſubſtantiation, they haue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen the definition of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? And that they haue polluted the Sacrament of Baptiſme, with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite corruptions? And that they haue taken awaye, euen at the firſte, one Element of the Supper of the Lorde? And whilſt that afterwarde by a more than abhominable wickedneſſe (chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging that Sacrament, into that dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable propitiatorie Sacrifice) they haue vtterly taken awaye, all that holy action, and therefore openly haue by violence pulled away the ſeale of the couenant of the new Teſtament? To be ſhorte, that they haue, by as many falſe Sacraments, as it pleaſed them to deuiſe, taken to them ſelues, the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Ieſus Chriſte, oure onely lawe gyuer? Therefore what parte of
<pb facs="tcp:1688:53"/> Gods worde, haue not theſe men cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, or rather cleane taken away? And then where is that onely, true, perpetuall and neceſſarye marke of the Catholique Churche? Where is that Seede, whiche beeing taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, the ſpreading of the Church alſo vppon earth, muſte needes be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way?</p>
            <p>Now, if the queſtion be, touching that Eccleſiaſticall gouernement (that I may ſpeake ſome what more fully of this matter, than heretofore I haue done) what I beſeeche you, can a man finde, in the Popiſhe cleargie, but that Image of the beaſt? Hath not this high Biſhoppe ſucceeded the other high By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of <hi>Rome,</hi> which was wont to be therin the hyre of the Gentiles? What ſay I? Hath not that Romiſhe Pope, ſnatched to him ſelfe, (by occupying nowe at the laſte, and in ſome ages here to ſore, by ſittinge in <hi>Rome</hi>) the verye name, and all the authoritie of the verie Emperour of <hi>Rome?</hi> For the thinges whiche yet remayne there, beeing Reliques not ſo muche
<pb facs="tcp:1688:54"/> of the Romaine empire, as of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Germane</hi> kingdome and gouernment, what are they more I pray you, but a bare ſhewe and name, not onely becauſe, the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours themſelues doe of their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord; at this day, worſhip the féet of this beaſt, but alſo, becauſe, he ſuffereth, not ſo much as one of his falſe cleargie, to be ſubiect, to any ſecular power, as they call it? yea rather who perceiueth not, this wicked fellow, not contented, with this ſo great wickedneſſe, to be the very ſame perſon, whom <hi>Paul</hi> fore told <hi>should</hi> ſit (after the empire of <hi>Rome</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed) <hi>In the temple of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>and exalt him ſelfe, aboue all that is called God?</hi> For is not this he, that openly affirmeth, that he muſte bee iudged of no man, no not of the Aungelles? Who (if his price be giuen him) boaſteth that he can open both heauen and hell? who at his pleaſure openly breaketh all lawes both of God and men? who alſo more than once, with in theſe few yeares, hath vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done lawes eſtabliſhed by nature it ſelfe: which wickedneſſe alſo the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane city of <hi>Rome</hi> in time here to fore,
<pb facs="tcp:1688:54"/> (in the raigne of <hi>Claudius</hi> the emperor) abhorred? who hath ſold euen for a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thoſe very canons, whoſe name was wont, to make a fraide the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant people.</p>
            <p>And as for thoſe purpled Cardinals, what other thing are they, than an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auncient ſenate of <hi>Rome,</hi> but of that ſenate which ſerued the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, and deuiding the gouernement betweene them: but who is ſo ignorant of the ſtate of <hi>Rome,</hi> that doth not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that that diſtribution of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is a picture of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> empire of <hi>Rome</hi> ouerthrown, which thing alſo the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> themſelues, and the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that be addicted to them, do wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? And as concerning other eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall functions, ſuch as they were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of Chriſt by his Apoſtles, what doth there remaine among them, but moſt vayne names and bare titles? For the office of a biſhop, which in the begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning, that is, while the Churche flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, was (as <hi>Hierome</hi> alſo witneſſeth) nothing els, but the office of an elder, whilſt euen immediatly after the time
<pb facs="tcp:1688:55"/> of the Apoſtles, it proceeded to thoſe heights of dignities (or as they them ſelues ſpeake) prelacies, (of which we haue before ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) is now a good while ago, wholly vaniſht awaye amongeſt them.</p>
            <p>Nowe what is it with them to bee a miniſter? Is it to be appointed to feede ſome flocke? Is it to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ouerſight of manners, and to beare rule in the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Church? No in deede, but to haue aucthoritie to offer Chriſt agayn? What is it to bee a Deacon? Is it to take charge of the goodes of the Church, and righty to diſpence them to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and the poore, and to render an account of that which is receiued and layde out? Fye, fie, for this (except al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wais the yéelding of accounts) is rather the onely chiefe and common office, to all of the whole Popiſh clergie, &amp; ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of the Pope himſelfe: and that ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly and ſo carefully indéede, or coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly rather exerciſed, that they exact, (euen of thoſe that bee deade manye yeeres before) a greate Tribute, and, vnto them that be aliue, they doe not
<pb facs="tcp:1688:55"/> fréely giue anye thing, though neuer ſo little. Therefore there is no ſuche, eyther Byſhoppe or Miniſter among them, as the apoſtle alloweth of: and as for Deacons, not ſo muche as one at all. And yet theſe bee the men, that obiecte vnto vs, the ſucceſſion of the Apoſtles. And if ſo bee, that that one olde Canon ſo often times repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the aunciente Synodes, and altogether agreeable to the woorde of God, did preuaile, to wit, that that ordination which is boughte by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney (that I may omit the principall parts of a iuſt eccleſiaſtical calling, that is to ſay, trial and election, ioined with the free conſent of the whole Churche, which are wholly aboliſhed by them, if a man conſider the thing it ſelfe,) ſhould be iudged I ſay, altogether void, what marke of Apoſtolicall ordination, ſhall there bee founde amongſt them? vnleſſe happelye they meane, that it is one and the ſelfe ſame thing, to mocke at the order inſtituted by the Apoſtles, and to keepe that Order
<pb facs="tcp:1688:56"/> diligently, which hath beene deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hand to hand: and vnleſſe they wold prooue, that lawfull and currant coyne, were to be knowen from counterfeit mony, by the bare image, grauen vpon it, and not rather, by the matter it ſelfe, eſpecially as often as, they ſhewe the ſame image to both parties.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort therefore, what maner of one is that Catholique church, in which in ſteed of true Chriſt, a moſt falſe idoll, at leaſt wiſe, in reſpect of his office, is ſet vp: and where in ſteed of Gods pure word, partly the traditions of men, and partly, the traditions of the Deuill are placed: and where alſo in ſteed of ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, &amp; Apoſtolicall ordination, nothing hath place all moſt but moſt manifeſt and deteſtable, euen to the Deuill him ſelfe as it were, both bying and ſelling of ſoules redéemed by the blood of Chriſt, in ſo muche that they woulde haue it to be accounted, an vnlawfull thinge to ſearche into theſe matters, yea ſo farre haue they procéeded that they would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne men (though their cauſe be not heard) yf high treaſon againſt God and
<pb facs="tcp:1688:56"/> man, wheras on the other ſide if a man ſhould graunt theſe things, there ſhold be nothing ſo wicked, ſo blaſphemous and ſo horrible to be thought, which a man might not with their good leaue &amp; liking, think, ſpeak, and write.</p>
            <p>But (theſe men wil ſay) although we were nothing leſſe, than we will ſéeme to be, doth it followe that the name of Catholique Church, which yee take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, doth agree vnto your Churches? No verely. Wherefore we haue in vayne now a long time agoe deſired triall to be made, by the matter it ſelfe,<note place="margin">That our Churches haue all the true markes of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church, and ſpecially the pure vvorde of God.</note> if their bare deniall may be accepted. We ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore affirme, that the three notes of the Catholique Church (to wit, the ſeede of the written worde, and the right and lawfull Eccleſiaſticall calling and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, all which we haue reſtored, are in our poſſeſſion, and ſtand on our ſide. Theſe things they ſtoutly deny. In déed this controuerſie cannot be decided in a few words, neither do I at this preſent goe about it. But that which I had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in hand to prooue, I hope I haue perfourmed, to wit, that the falſe and
<pb facs="tcp:1688:57"/> counterfeit notes of the Church, which they alleaged, are ſufficiently confuted, and the true notes of the Churche ſet forth and approoued.</p>
            <p>For it is one thing, to diſpute of thoſe markes, which they are, and another to diſpute, who haue them. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, becauſe I haue in few wordes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that they haue not thoſe marks, this thing alſo I may now ſpeake, that we haue at leaſt, two very waighty con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectures, which make for vs agaynſte them: to wit, that in diſcerning and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of opinions, we ſtay our ſelues, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the only written word of God, that is, the writings of the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles? and that we require the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of it, by the onely conference of places, and proportion of the articles of fayth. Neither do we refuſe the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges of any, either old or new author, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may be examined, by the rules afore ſayd: by Gods worde, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of faith. But what theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect againſt theſe vpright requeſtes, it ſufficiently appeareth.</p>
            <p>Now in the queſtion of ſucceſſion and
<pb facs="tcp:1688:57"/> ordination, they haue thought that not many yeares agoe, they haue found out,<note place="margin">That our Churches, haue the true Apoſtolicall ſucceſſion.</note> a more certain reaſon to diſpute againſt vs. For they demaund euen with great loftineſſe and pride, that we ſhoulde ſhew them, whom they haue ſucceeded, which in our times haue eſtabliſhed our Churches, as though we were no better able, to ſhew our original, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Donatistes</hi> coulde theirs. We aunſwere that the doctrine which we defend, hath (euen from the time of the Apoſtles, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hereſies haue aſſaulted it, &amp; the Romiſh falſe biſhops, and others, made drunke by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harlot, haue by al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> means they could, and that for the ſpace of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine yeres polluted it) continued notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding, euen vntill our times, &amp; ſhall continue, euen to the end of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world: and that about 200 yeeres ſince this light of the Goſpell began againe, (and that thorow the ſingular goodnes of God) in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weſt to apeare, out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> filth of popery, &amp; thoſe hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> places, into which theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had thruſt it, vntill y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>delſticks, which were take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, were ſet again in their places, &amp; by that means the elect people
<pb facs="tcp:1688:58"/> of God, did from all quarters flow to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnto the ſayd truth.</p>
            <p>But as concerning the ſucceſſion of the holy miniſtery,<note place="margin">2. The. 2.7.</note> we ſay, <hi>that that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery of iniquity (which the Apostle witneſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth in his time to haue beene begun,</hi> was not accompliſhed, but in ſome proceſſe &amp; length of time, and therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that old Church of <hi>Rome</hi> became, &amp; that but by little &amp; litle, of Apoſtolical, Apoſtatical, that is, fallen from the truth: and we af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that other Churches (as it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by hiſtories) did not ſtraightwaies fall away from the foundation, but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verely, when as in the church, the falſe biſhop,<note place="margin">2. The. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>and ſonne of perdition in deed,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him ſelfe the vniuerſall head of the Church) did at the length, <hi>exalt himſelfe aboue all that is called God.</hi> And that this was don when the kings and Princes, yea, and the very Paſtors them ſelues, in other countries, being bewitched by this harlot, had ſubmitted them ſelues to the feet of <hi>Antichrist.</hi> Now, when, &amp; by what degrees and ſleights that hath bene brought to paſſe, cannot elſe wher be better not only known, but euen per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb facs="tcp:1688:58"/> almoſt by the very eyes, than by the very liues of the biſhops the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, declared by good and ſufficient writers: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euents and falling out of things iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye agrreing with the foretellinges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> expoſitions of the lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, both ancient, and alſo certaine new writers, which our very aduerſaries, dare not refuſe, in ſo much that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which the Apoſtle heretofore ſpake of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.24.</note> 
               <hi>that his Goſpell was had in deed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them that should perish, &amp; whome the God of this world had blinded, that the light of the Goſpel of the glory of Christ should not shine vpon them,</hi> the ſame we may now moſt truely affirme of this wicked An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian ſinck, faining or pretending the name of the Catholique Churche. Therefore we haue next after the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, for ſucceſſors, thoſe very right iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging paſtors, not onely of the <hi>Roman</hi> church, but of other churches alſo, whoſe ſucceſſion (beeing broken of by theſe wolues &amp; tirants) we haue begun tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Gods goodnes at the laſt to reſtore: ſo farre of is it, either that we are deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the lawful argument of ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:1688:59"/> or that they ſhoulde bee able to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage any Apoſtolicall ſucceſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">That the Catholique Church hath bene, and in ſome reſpect as yet is, in the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome thogh the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome be not the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique church nor any part thereof. Math. 21.33.34.</note>Therefore ſay theſe men, where was that Catholique viſible Church, aboute two hundred yeres paſt? Chriſt himſelf maketh anſwere for vs, that it hath bin heretofore, and as yet in ſome reſpecte is, <hi>in the handes of the wicked buſbande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> who themſelues, <hi>ſlewe the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes of the Lorde, being ſent vnto them, and with all, as much as they coulde, euen the Sonne himſelfe, beeing cast oute of the Vineyard:</hi> and in ſteede of him, they haue placed a Chriſt in words, wherwith thei mocke the people, but in deede euerye one, euen the wickedſt of theire owne ſort, that they can or could get. But it is well, that neyther the eternall kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of that vine, can againe in déede be caſte out, neither could againe be ſlaine. who liueth vnto God, and who alſo nowe againe appearing, hath begun, to lette out that Vineyard, to good and faithfull huſbandmen, <hi>Paule</hi> alſo aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth in oure behalfe, foretelling that which wee ſée fulfilled: To wit, that that wicked one, ſhoulde <hi>vſurpe to
<pb facs="tcp:1688:59"/> him ſelf the Temple of the Lorde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>vntill the Lorde shoulde agayne diſcouer him. Iohn alſo aunſwereth that that woman, hauing lately brought foorth hir Childe, bath togeather with hir Childe, layen hidden in the wilderneſſe, free from the Dragon, who trusted to, and vſed alſo, and was euen as it were vpholde with the power of Kinges and Princes: And that that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Citye, hath in the meane time conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſure, not for a ſmale time, but for two and forty monethes, or a thouſand two hundred and ſixty dayes.</hi> But we leaue the acccount of thoſe dayes to ſharper witted men: we vrge onely the matter it ſelfe. Therefore, to ſpeake plainely, we ſay, that ſo long as that great <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaell</hi> did appeare by little and little, killing that Dragon with the ſwoorde of his worde (which hee hath agayne committed to his faythfull ſeruauntes) or with the ſpirite of his mouth, that ſo long the Catholique Churche, (that is to ſaye, euery number though neuer ſo ſmal, of ſuch as helde faſt both the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonne, and alſo the office of the true Chriſte) laye hidde in the filthineſſes
<pb facs="tcp:1688:60"/> of the <hi>Romiſh Babylon,</hi> whileſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked one with his angels, vſurping the ſeate of the miniſtery, and the harlot that ſate vpon the ſeuen hilles, did make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world drunke with her dreggs.</p>
            <p>But they ſay, that this true Churche, ought always to be viſible.</p>
            <p>To this, if I ſhall aunſwere, that the true Church indeed, hath alwaies beene viſible, and ſo ſhall be, ſo farre forth as ſhe conſiſteth, of true viſible members, and that it is not a counterfayte thing:<note place="margin">In what ſenſe the true Church is called vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</note> and alſo that it is viſible ſo farre forth, as it hath outward and euident marks: &amp; yet not in ſuch ſorte viſible: as though they that embrace true religion, ſhould always ſo agree, that euery man might pointe out with this finger, both who they are, and where they are: if I ſaye I ſhall aunſwere this, I ſhall indeede ſpeake, as the matter is, and that which I haue a little before, by reaſons and examples declared. But I make not this place my refuge: for I ſaye, that if wee will fetch recordes, euen from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles themſelues (who haue as it were with their finger poynted oute this
<pb facs="tcp:1688:60"/> wicked one, and all his falſe Church) that then we ſhall find, that there ſcarce hath beene any age, but that therein, ſo ſoone as this Antichriſte began to ſhew his head, the Lord hath alwayes ſtirred vp ſome, who did ſet themſelues againſt his tyrannie. If they denie this thing, let them laye a wager, but withall let them giue pledges or ſureties for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmaunce, &amp; I doubt not but we ſhall ſhew foorth euen to al men, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the thing is ſo (vnleſſe they had rather be willing<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly blynd) yea and that by good and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient witneſſes, and by cleare, euident, and manifeſt teſtimonies, drawen out of their very owne courtes and records.</p>
            <p>But the aduerſaries cannot ſo be bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deled, but that they will reply,<note place="margin">That the true laying on of hands remayneth vvholy with vs.</note> deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at the laſt, what laying on of ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds we are able to alleadge, that they haue receiued, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in our time our chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches haue bene eſtabliſhed. For ſo I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, <hi>Spenſa,</hi> a Doctor of the <hi>Sorbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistes,</hi> did cry out againſt vs, by whome afterward there was publiſhed concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning theſe matters, a voulome verye groſſe, and full of ſlaunders.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1688:61"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hovv farre forth the lay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing on of handes hath beene coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted neceſſari to a lavvfull calling.</note>Firſt, I anſwere that, which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe elſwhere hath noted out of <hi>Hierom,</hi> againſt the<note n="*" place="margin">So called of one Lucifer, vvho helde that the ſoul vvas of the ſubſtance of the flesh.</note> 
               <hi>Luciferians,</hi> which place al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Gratian</hi> hath put into his decrees: to wit, that the laying on of handes after baptiſme perteineth rather to the honor of prieſthood (as they call it) than to bind anye by neceſſitye of lawe, to obſerue it. After this ſort therefore I ſaye, did <hi>Hierome</hi> iudge whome they call vppon amongſte their Sayntes. But they will replye forſooth that he diſputeth of laying on of haneds in confirmation, and not of laying on of handes in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, as they are woonte to ſpeake. Whiche that I maye graunte to bee ſo, (although <hi>Spenſa</hi> thoughte otherwiſe) what ſhall this replication or excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion helpe them? for they themſelues do not onely number confirmation among the Sacraments, but alſo (when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them) they account it more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, than Baptiſme it ſelfe. But let vs omit this thing. They confeſſe (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they will diſſent from <hi>Bernard,</hi> in his Epiſtle 77. who notwithſtanding, ſtandeth bothe vppon the worde of God,
<pb facs="tcp:1688:61"/> and alſo vppon the authoritie of <hi>Austen</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) that thoſe whiche are of the yeeres of diſcretion, are blotted out of the Churche, for contempt of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and not for the want of it. And what ſhall let vs, that wee maye not muche more ſpeake the ſame thing, of the laying on of handes, vſed in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing orders? vnleſſe peraduenture, they ſhall ſaye, that that is more to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired vnto the holy Miniſterye, than Baptiſme vnto ſaluation. But howe can theſe excellent ſeruauntes of God, ſeeme to haue contemned the laying on of handes, which in our time, by a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye Heauenlye inſpiration, haue deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the Churche from the Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye of Antichriſte, when as they had none, of whome they could lawfully, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by the warrant of the olde Canons themſelues, aſke, or receiue the ſame? for I haue before ſhewed, &amp; yet affirme this thing, that there can not be found one amongſt the whole clergie of <hi>Rome,</hi> which is able, by the pure and auncient canons, to defend their ordination to be lawfull. What ſay I? It appeareth that
<pb facs="tcp:1688:62"/> euen in the moſt pure Churche alſo, the laying on of handes, was not counted ſo neceſſary? for who I beſech you laid his hands vpon <hi>Philip,</hi> that of a Deacon he ſhold be made an Euangeliſt?<note place="margin">Act. 8.4.</note> who laid handes vpon them, in that firſte diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of them ſelues abroad at <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> (the very Apoſtles alſo being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant therof) preached the Goſpell with ſo great fruit in <hi>Samaria?</hi> but theſe men. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> were afterwarde ſent, who ſhould lay their hands vpon them.<note place="margin">Act. 8.14.</note> Yea for ſooth vppon thoſe who beléeued and were baptiſed, for as for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which firſt had preached the Goſpell vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: there is no mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at all made of them. But let vs put the caſe that this place were to be vnderſtood of theſe men alſo. The Apoſtles therefore ratified that, which the other as occaſion ſerued had done, euen before examination, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ordinary election, not meaning to make the laying on of hands, to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary. And if theſe men be the ſucceſſors of the Apoſtles (as they will be called and accounted) why haue not they them ſelues alſo, &amp; that by the
<pb facs="tcp:1688:62"/> example of the Apoſtles, made haſte, to approoue at the leaſt, the zeale of godly men? Or why did they not helpe, the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of that Archbiſhop of <hi>Colen,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhould haue betrayed him to that Romiſh <hi>Antichrist?</hi> for a reward alſo, of which wicked déed <hi>Gropperus</hi> had the Cardinals hat beſtowed vpon him, a couer in deed worthy for ſuche a cup. For ſooth (they will ſay) becauſe ye are heretiques. Therfore the queſtion muſt be of the doctrine and not of the laying on of handes, and then (as I hope) we ſhall get the victory.</p>
            <p>But they will againe reply that that thing was lawfull at the firſt, when the Churches were ſpringing: but now an order beeing once eſtabliſhed, the ſame thing is not lawfull. I aunſwere that I confeſſe, there ought great regard, to be had of the times, &amp; that they are not to be borne with all, who violate the lawes of the Church, beeing well eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blſhed. But what if I ſhall ſay that the lawes of right and lawfull ordination are not violated by vs, but that (when they were taken away and defaced by
<pb facs="tcp:1688:63"/> them, that fayned them ſelues to be the keepers of that order) we haue applyed our ſelues to the reſtitution, and reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of them? For, that this thing is ſo, it appeareth by this, that (excepting the ceremonies which are iuſtly abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated) al thinges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded in the word of God, and preſcribed in the auncient pure canons, are obſerued exactly in our Churches, but amongſt them, manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neglected. Now, who, when Paſtors by common conſent, are chaunged into Wolues, woulde ſaye, that the ſheepe ſhoulde looke for ſuch manner of ayde, from Wolues: and that ſhoulde bee condemned, whiche after the example of the Prophets, doth willingly ſet him ſelfe againſte wolues? Let this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie therefore be firſte diſputed of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the queſtion be made, touching the forme of ordination: and let theſe men leaue of to boaſt of the apparell and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſhewe of Paſtors, when <hi>as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly they be rauening wolues.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.15.</note> Verely Chriſt commandeth true Paſtors to be diſtinguiſhed from falſe, not by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.16.</note> 
               <hi>But by their fruits,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is,
<pb facs="tcp:1688:63"/> by doctrin and maners. But what wil their Paſtors that be made, by Bulles and licences, anſwere to theſe things?</p>
            <p>They being inforced, to condemne extraordinary vocations,<note place="margin">That mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles are not neceſſary to prooue anye holy, lavvfull vocation, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie or extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie.</note> and that more than once, and without exception alſo, at the laſte they flie vnto myracles, which they will haue of neceſſitie to be requyred, to this extraordinary vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But if a man bydde them alleadge, oute of what place of Scripture, they haue at the length drawen this rule: then it neceſſarily followeth, eyther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they can ſpeake no more than fyſhes, or els bewraie extreem ſhameleſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Now, firſte it is manifeſt that the gyfte of myracles, hath alwayes beene free, that is, ſet in the power of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, who hath gyuen the ſame at cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne tymes, and to certaine perſons: Therefore we can make no rule of it. Next, ſeeing that not onely Chriſt hath foretolde, but alſo the olde and new ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes witneſſe, that this gyft, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon both to true, and alſo to falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, what madneſſe ſhall it argue, to bee deſirous to haue the falſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:1688:64"/> to be diſcerned from the true, by miracles?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">By vvhat meanes falſe vocations may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note>Then you will ſay, it ſhall be lawful for euery one to teach in the Church? no in deed. For who ſoeuer (where there is place for order) diſpiſeth that order, he declareth by this very thing, that he is not of God and therfore not to be heard. Therefore the <hi>Donatistes,</hi> who were in deed <hi>Schiſmatiques,</hi> are by this reaſon iuſtly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned, becauſe, though it had bene moſt true, which they obiected vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Occilianus,</hi> yet the order of the church, was not for that cauſe to be broken, and they were not to be borne with, when for the defection of ſome Churches, they cryed out, that all the world was fallen away. But where a generall diſorder, vnder the ſhew of order, beareth ſway, and no remedy can be looked for, from the authours of this miſchiefe: then doubtleſſe, this muſt be performed that euen as when a fier is rayſed in a City, thoſe men ceſſing, or ſetting the city it ſelfe a fier, which by the ordinances of the city, ought to haue come to the quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of that fier, it is the part of euery
<pb facs="tcp:1688:64"/> good Citizen, to carrye water, yea euen without order, and to caſt it vppon the flames: ſo in this, much more da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous fire of the Temple of the Lorde, it is the duetie of euery godly man, as muche as in him lieth, to ſet him ſelf againſt that euil: and alſo of the godly magiſtrate, to prouide that a lawfull order bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored. So haue the godly Prophets in times paſt done: ſo haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly kinges <hi>Ezechias</hi> and <hi>Ioſias</hi> done: and vnleſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very chriſtian Emperors, when hereſies bare greate ſway, had interpoſed their authoritie, none had more beaten down the Church (as at the length we ſée it to haue bene done) than they that gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the chiefeſt ſeates. And if notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this, there haue beene no ordinary vocation, in the times of theſe ancient Synodes, we muſte know that that fell out in deed, becauſe, that a law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful order then eſtabliſhed in the church, was not altogeather aboliſhed, as it is manifeſt that it hath beene performed, now ſundry ages ſince, thorow the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of the falſe Romiſh Biſhop: ther remayning amongeſt them not ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:1688:65"/> as a very ſlender ſhadow of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall parts of Eccleſiaſticall vocacion: to wit, of triall and election: but (after a moſt filthy ſale of all thinges), they v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing onely a vicelike kinde of laying on of hands, thereby to deceiue the comon people.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">VVe vvant not euen that laying on of hands vvhich the falſe church of Rome, doth vntru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to a lavvfull cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note>But though theſe thinges were not forcible (which indeed are yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding moſt ſtrong) what doth an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary vocation appertaine to vs? For it is moſt manifeſt, that thoſe firſte reſtorers of Gods houſe, in the dayes of our forefathers: to wit, <hi>Wickliffe, Hus, Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prage, Luther, Bucer, Oecolam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padius, Swinglius, Pellican, Haller,</hi> and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many other) had the ſelfe ſame lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands that theſe men require, giuen them by their Biſhops, to teache the people: by whome afterwardes the Churches were, by little and little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored: In which Churches alſo, we af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that the true vocation of paſtors, Doctors, and Deacons, was reſtored. Now I call that a true calling, which is according to the preſcript of Gods word.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1688:65"/>
            <p>But here againe our vnorderly ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries ſuppoſe,<note place="margin">The laying on of hands, belongeth to the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biterie and not to that ſtate of By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops which men haue deuiſed.</note> that they haue found out ſomewhat, wherin they may manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blame vs. For they deny, that albeit thoſe men, whom euen now we named, were miniſters, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therfore we are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ordayned, ſeeing that biſhops one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may ordayne miniſters, muche leſſe ſay they, can we be biſhops. I in deed do willingly leaue vnto them, al this ſtate of biſhoppely gouernment, whereof I plainely ſay, that the holy Ghoſt was not the aucthor, but mans wiſedome, and vppon which, vnleſſe we perceiue that God hath layed a curſe, verely we do as yet ſee nothing at all: and we fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter a Viper in our boſome, which will again kill the mother. But of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we will ſpeake in an other place.</p>
            <p>Now onely I demaund of theſe men, from whence they haue fet this: for ſooth from the ſecond Canon of the Apoſtles, (as they call it). But <hi>Gelaſius</hi> the Pope him ſelfe doth recken theſe Canons, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the writinges counted <hi>Apocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha:</hi> to wit I ſuppoſe, at the leaſt for the titles ſake. For he muſt needes be too
<pb facs="tcp:1688:66"/> impudent, that woulde deny theſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, to haue bene made in more ages than one, ſo farr is it of, that ridiculous inuention (attributed to I cannot tel to what <hi>Clement,</hi> and lately publiſhed in <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> in which the Apoſtles are brought in one by one eſtablſhing theſe matters, may bee allowed of any man that is of any ſound ſenſe or iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But to what end ſhould we han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle theſe thinges ſo largely? That the Euangeliſts were aboue the miniſters of which we ſpeake (for otherwiſe <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, calleth euen him ſelfe a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low miniſter with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1.) theſe men dare not deny, becauſe the Apoſtle him ſelfe ſetteth them before Paſtors and Doctors. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11. But euen <hi>Paul</hi> him ſelfe witneſſeth, that <hi>Timothie,</hi> not appointed a Biſhop to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> or any other Churche, but an Euangeliſt, and the companion of <hi>Paule</hi> the Apoſtle, did not receiue the impoſition, or laying on of handes, no not from <hi>Paule</hi> him ſelfe, but from the preſbiterie, that is, from the companie or felowſhippe of Elders. Wherfore if theſe men that mind to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb facs="tcp:1688:66"/> the falſe biſhoply tyrannie, be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to reaſon, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſpute not with <hi>Geminianus</hi> (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ciuil lawiers are wont to ſay) but with <hi>Paul</hi> him ſelfe. We ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely thinke thoſe to be lawfully orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, who hauing according to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles rule, and exact inquirie of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and maners going before, and a free and holy election, by the conſent of the whole Churche, which they are to gouerne, are conſecrated and dedicated to God by ſolemne prayes, and the very rite of laying on of handes vſed (if men ſhall ſo thinke good) but yet ſimple, and of it ſelfe, and not defiled with any tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing theſe things are ſo,<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the vvhole Treatie.</note> I ſay that the fauourers of the falſe Romiſhe Churche, doe in vayne ſet out or obiect, thoſe three notes of the Church: to wit, ſucceſſion méerely perſonall, a calling ſundred from the doctrine of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: and the laying on of hands. And I ſay this, both becauſe that none of theſe by it ſelfe, can be either, a true, or ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple neceſſary, or perpetuall note of the vniuerſal Church: and alſo, becauſe that
<pb facs="tcp:1688:67"/> though it were ſo, yet that no one of theſe notes at all, can be founde, in the falſe Romiſhe Church, which doth not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding cal hir ſelfe, (though moſt falſely,) the vniuerſall Church: and on the other ſide I affirme, that that onely, true, neceſſary and perpetuall marke of the Catholique Churche, that is to ſay, that doctrine, which is moſt perfectly contayned in the wrytings of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes and Apoſtles, doth once agayne ſhine bright and cleere in our Churches: and to be ſhorte, that the very perſonall ſucceſſion, vocation, and ordination of the holy and right miniſtrie, are reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the ſame our Churches: and that we haue not forſaken <hi>Syon,</hi> but haue <hi>fled out of Babylon</hi> as the Lorde warneth vs:<note place="margin">Reuel. 18.4.</note> &amp; that, wee haue not rent in ſunder the Church, but following <hi>Pauls</hi> fact, in the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> mentioned <hi>Acts.</hi> 19.9. <hi>haue ſeperated Diſciples to the Lord:</hi> and that we haue not by the example of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 16.10. &amp;c.</note> or the <hi>Donatistes,</hi> ſet vp <hi>altar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst altar, but casting the altar brought</hi> from <hi>Damaſcus</hi> out of the Lordes houſe, we haue begun to reſtore the true and
<pb facs="tcp:1688:67"/> ſincere worſhip of God, which worke alſo I hope (although Sathan, do by his miniſters ſet himſelfe againſt the ſame, both within the Church, and without it) ſhall yet notwithſtanding <hi>(when that ſonne of perdition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>shall at the last be thorowly ouerthrowen, by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Gods mouth)</hi> be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly atchieued and finiſhed.</p>
            <trailer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London by Robert Walde-graue, dwelling with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> Temple-barre, in the Stronde, neere vnto Somet-ſet houſe.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
